So, today, I called this meeting because,
Bugün bu toplantıyı,
which is a big announcement of Gregoire getting married.
Gregoire'in evleneceğine dair büyük bir duyuru yapmak için ayarladım.
And he’s been very sweet to his bride.
Gelinine karşı çok tatlı davrandı.
I liked it.
Bu hoşuma gitti.
He was very gentle and nice
Çok nazik ve kibardı.
and really took it in the proper sense.
Ve durumu gerçekten doğru bir şekilde algıladı.
And Rajesh also came with his ‘fiance’.
Rajesh de nişanlısıyla birlikte geldi.
He is getting married on the 12th.
O, ayın on ikisinde evlenecek.
And then another thing is
Ve bir diğer konu ise,
about how to develop England and Europe together.
İngiltere ve Avrupa'yı birlikte nasıl geliştirebileceğimiz hakkında.
In England, a very substantial force is there, no doubt.
İngiltere'de şüphesiz çok önemli bir güç var.
But we have to think about how to propagate.
Ama nasıl yaygınlaştıracağımızı düşünmeliyiz.
Now I have thought of one or two things which are lacking in Sahaja Yoga in here, I think.
Sahaja Yoga'da burada eksik olduğunu düşündüğüm bir iki şey var.
One of them is we have no publicity done.
Bunlardan biri, tanıtım yapmamamız.
We have not been able to get people for publicity.
Tanıtım için insan bulamadık.
Now this Times fellow; before I leave, we have to do something about it.
Şimdi bu Times adamı… Ben ayrılmadan önce bununla ilgili bir şeyler yapmalıyız.
You can take it and note it down, it would be better.
Bunu alabilirsiniz ve not alabilirsiniz. Daha iyi olur.
Note it.
Not alın.
[Sahaja Yogis talking]
[Sahaja Yogiler konuşuyor]
[Unclear] it is better be written down some points, will be better.
Bazı noktaları yazmak daha iyi olur. Arkamdan...
Behind Me, paper and pencil, you take it.
Kağıt ve kalem, alın.
[Sahaja Yogis talking]
Sahaja Yogi: Peki, buraya neyi kaydetmek gerekiyor?
It’s better to
Yazmak daha iyi olur.
write it down, in short.
Kısaca…
Agnya? All
Agnya? Pekâlâ... Herkes sol Agnya'yı hissediyor.
right.
Ona bakın...
Everybody is catching Left Agnya.
Elleriyle deniyor…
I mean cover her feet or if you have socks, it’s better.
Yani ayaklarını örtün ya da çoraplarınız varsa... Daha iyi olur.
It is getting blue with that.
O yüzden maviye dönüyor.
Hmm…it’s cold.
Hmm… Soğuk.
So, first this gentleman, what was his name,
Yani, önce bu beyefendi... Adı neydi?
was ‘Mascareness’ or whatever it was, to be contacted.
"Mascareness" ya da her neyse, onunla iletişime geçilecek.
And there is a doctor in Geneva who has taken lot of interest.
Ve Cenevre'de çok ilgilenen bir doktor var.
His name is Dr. Masca.
Adı Dr. Masca.
In his presence, I cured about 5 people.
Onun yanında yaklaşık 5 kişiyi iyileştirdim.
So, he said that he didn’t deliberate in My presence.
O da Benim huzurumda düşünmediğini söyledi.
I said, “All right “.
Ben de "Tamam" dedim.
And he is going to study those things.
Ve o bu konuları araştıracak.
So, you tell Gregoire to get after him
Yani, Gregoire'a onun bu insanları
that he goes and sees these people.
görmeye gittiğinden emin olmasını söyleyin.
And they should try to convince the people whom I’ve cured,
Ve onlar Benim iyileştirdiğim insanları,
that by giving something in writing,
yazılı bir şey vererek, Sahaja Yoga ile diğer insanların iyileşmesine
they will be helping other people to get cured of Sahaja Yoga.
yardımcı olacaklarına ikna etmeye çalışmalılar.
You see, this is the only way we can really approach these gross people.
Görüyorsunuz bu, bu kaba insanlara gerçekten yaklaşabileceğimiz tek yol.
So, he is going to give an article starting with this,
Bu yüzden, bu mucizeyi gördüğünü anlatan bir makale yazacak.
that he saw this miracle.
Bu mucizeyi gördüğünü anlatan bir makale yazacak.
Then he saw the raising of the Kundalini.
Sonra Kundalini'nin yükseldiğini gördü. Ve o gördü…
He saw the – I mean the kind of an article you would like to publish.
Makaleyi hangi çizgide yayınlayacağımızı hazırlamalısınız.
We have, of course, concrete examples you can give,
Elbette verebileceğiniz somut örnekler var.
he being a doctor, you see.
O bir doktor, anlarsınız ya...
It will have an effect and that we should publish it in England,
Bu etkili olacaktır ve bunu İngiltere'de yayınlamalıyız.
because he was also practicing here.
Çünkü o da burada çalışıyordu.
He has a house in this merrily ground road or somewhere.
Bu neşeli yolun üzerinde veya başka bir yerde bir evi var.
So, we can publish in his name.
Yani, onun adına yayınlayabiliriz.
So one of the advantages would be,
Böylece, avantajlarından biri şu olur:
that he being a sort of an authorized person,
Kendisi bir bakıma yetkili bir kişi olduğu için,
you can publish this article about Sahaja Yoga in his name.
Sahaja Yoga ile ilgili bu makaleyi onun adıyla yayımlayabilirsiniz.
And we can contact Mr. Mascar.
Ve Bay Mascar ile iletişime geçebiliriz.
Then, in case we are successful, we can have a press conference or something,
Sonra eğer başarılı olursak, bir basın toplantısı veya
before I leave, if possible.
benzeri bir şeyler düzenleyebiliriz,  mümkünse Ben ayrılmadan önce...
Or when I come back, one of them
Ya da Ben döndüğümde bunlardan birini yaparız;
and we have to work it out in such a way, that we also have a press conference, later on.
ve işi öyle bir şekilde ayarlamalıyız ki, daha sonra da bir basın toplantısı yapabilelim.
For publicity, you see, what we have found that this poster business works out wonders.
Tanıtım için, gördük ki bu afiş işi gerçekten harikalar yaratıyor.
So, when I come back, we have to think on those lines of posters.
Yani, geri döndüğümde, bu posterler konusunda düşünmeliyiz.
And we can get very good posters done in India, if you want,
Ve isterseniz, Hindistan'da çok iyi posterler yaptırabiliriz
and can get them by the ship.
ve gemiyle getirebiliriz.
But if they arrive after four years, don’t blame Me.
Ama dört yıl sonra gelirlerse, Beni suçlamayın.
[Laughter]
Yayınlayabileceğiniz
Find out all the methods by which you can publish.
tüm yöntemleri araştırın.
Now, Gregoire’s book, we can take to some publisher
Gregoire'in kitabını bir yayıncıya götürüp
and ask him if he would like to publish.
yayınlamak isteyip istemediğini sorabiliriz.
Then what about Don’s book?
Peki ya Don'un kitabı?
That has to be ready before I leave,
O kitap Ben ayrılmadan önce hazır olmalı,
so we’ll get it published in India.
bu yüzden Hindistan'da yayınlatacağız.
[Shri Mataji chuckles]
Evet,
Yes, so what’s happening now?
şimdi ne oluyor?
The little dolly baby?
Küçük bebek mi?
She knows her Mother.
'Anne'sini tanıyor.
She knows her Mother very well.
'Anne'sini çok iyi tanıyor.
So, when we have,
Yani, sahip olduğumuzda… Demek istediğim;
I mean, we should all sit down
hepimiz oturup Sahaja Yoga hakkında
and find out how we can publish about or sort of advertise about Sahaja Yoga.
nasıl tanıtım yapabileceğimizi veya nasıl reklam yapabileceğimizi bulmalıyız.
You see, because even ordinary thing like punk crop or something, you know,
Çünkü punk saç kesimi gibi sıradan şeyler bile,
that goes into the eyes of these people, because they create a controversy.
bu insanların gözüne batıyor. Çünkü tartışma yaratıyorlar.
Now, you can start a lecture CDs on the false gurus.
Şimdi, sahte gurular hakkında bir konferans CD'si hazırlayabilirsiniz.
You people can go ahead with it.
Sizler bunu yapabilirsiniz.
You can go on talking about ‘this false guru is like this’, ‘that false guru is like this’
"Bu sahte guru şöyledir, o sahte guru böyledir", diye konuşmaya devam edebilirsiniz
and nowadays another thing they started is ‘magnetism’.
ve günümüzde başlattıkları başka bir şey daha var: "Manyetizma".
They put a magnetism and with the photograph of the guru.
Bir manyetik ve gurunun fotoğrafını koyuyorlar.
And they turn the magnet in a different way, you see,
Ve mıknatısı farklı bir şekilde çeviriyorlar, görüyorsunuz ya,
and then the bhoot comes in.
ve sonra bhoot geliyor.
I mean so many ways they will use, I don’t know,
Yani, pek çok yol kullanıyorlar, bilemiyorum,
but this is one of the latest I have seen.
ama bu gördüğüm en son şeylerden biri.
So, you see all this.
Yani, tüm bunları görüyorsunuz.
And there is another thing is that, they get the
Ve bir başka şey de,
photographs of the terrestrial or some sort of a being, you see,
dünyevi bir varlğın veya bir tür varlığın fotoğraflarını alıyorlar… Görüyorsunuz…
out of which, most surprising, the God who is on this earth had my eyes,
Ve en şaşırtıcı olanı, bu dünyadaki Tanrı Benim gözlerime sahipti
and as if the photograph is taken from here.
ve sanki fotoğraf buradan çekilmiş gibi.
So, the nose is like that and there is a mike in front.
Yani, burun böyle ve önünde bir mikrofon var.
I don’t know from where they got this idea!
Bu fikri nereden aldıklarını bilmiyorum!
The lady showed Me.
Bayan Bana gösterdi.
I said, “You’d better write to them. They can find out”.
Ben de "Onlara yazsan iyi olur. Onlar öğrenebilirler." dedim.
I mean, look at to what point they are!
Yani, bakın ne noktaya geldiler!
This is so subtle.
Bu çok subtil bir ayrıntı.
Now, so, for this, I could say that Peter, he has to go around.
Şimdi, bunun için Peter'in etrafta dolaşması gerektiğini söyleyebilirim.
So, I will first give you the way it should be done is you write to Marie.
Önce size nasıl yapılması gerektiğini söyleyeyim, Marie'ye yazın.
She wants to go there, Marie.
Marie oraya gitmek istiyor.
In Switzerland, everybody wants to know about TM.
İsviçre'de herkes Transandantal Meditasyon hakkında bilgi almak istiyor.
And they said they can arrange lectures for you.
Ve sizin için konuşma düzenleyebileceklerini söylediler.
But there is one doctor in Germany, who is very anxious to meet you.
Ama Almanya'da sizinle tanışmak için çok hevesli olan bir doktor var.
He is the head, sort of a head in [unclear] or someplace.
O, [belirsiz] ya da başka bir yerde bir tür başkan.
Sahaja Yogi: Really?
Sahaja Yogi: Gerçekten mi?
Shri Mataji: Yes.
Shri Mataji: Evet.
This doctor, his name I forgot.
Bu doktorun adını unuttum.
And he says, “No, no there are 20 names and this and that”.
Ve diyor ki, "Hayır, hayır, 20 isim var ve şu bu…"
But I told you.
Ama sana söyledim.
But he has got his Realization surprisingly,
Ama bunca saçmalığa rağmen,
despite the head of a nonsense. I tell you.
şaşırtıcı bir şekilde aydınlanmasını almış. Sana söylüyorum.
It’s so gracious, Sahaja Yoga is so gracious with people actually.
Bu çok lütufkâr. Sahaja Yoga insanlara karşı gerçekten çok lütufkâr.
[Shri Mataji chuckles]
Böyle bir adam,
Such a man like that, who has been in Sahaja Yoga for years.
yıllardır Sahaja Yoga'da.
Ten years or so. He is the head of that thing there.
On yıl kadar.
He
Oradaki şeyin başkanı…
got Realization all right.
Aydınlanmasını sorunsuzca aldı.
Sahaja Yogi: Mother, you can’t remember his name?
Sahaja Yogi: Anne, adını hatırlamıyor musunuz?
Shri Mataji: So, I’ve forgotten.
Shri Mataji: Evet, unuttum.
But they will all write to – Gregoire is going to write to you.
Ama hepsini sana yazacaklar… Gregoire sana yazacak.
Thomas. Thomas was so sweet.
Thomas. Thomas çok tatlıydı.
His wife was, ‘wife’ means his friend, was quite opposing Sahaja Yoga,
Karısı… "Karısı" derken arkadaşı demek istiyorum, Sahaja Yoga'ya oldukça karşıydı.
and, but still he organized on his own and very, very sweet he was.
Ama yine de kendi başına organize etti ve çok çok tatlıydı.
And I mean, he didn’t have much money but still we arranged all that.
Yani, çok parası yoktu ama yine de her şeyi ayarladık.
Bbut the rest of it was so sweet he did.
Ama yaptığı diğer her şey o kadar tatlıydı ki…
And, very sensible. He is a very good man.
Ve çok duyarlı. Çok iyi bir adam.
And another was, another was Jack, you remember Jack?
Bir diğeri de Jack'ti. Jack'i hatırlıyor musun?
The one who came with his wife, who would not give her name.
Karısıyla birlikte gelen, karısının adını vermeyen adam.
But this girl from Sydney did not meet Me.
Ama Sydney'den gelen bu kız Benim ile tanışmadı.
(Sahaja Yogi talking).
(Sahaja Yogi konuşuyor)
Huh? Oh! That’s it! Carrie.
Shri Mataji: Ha? Oh! İşte bu, Carrie.
Sahaja Yogi: Another Carrie”.
Sahaja Yogi:  Başka bir Carrie.
Shri Mataji: Yeah. Australia is doing very well.
Shri Mataji: Evet. Avustralya çok iyi gidiyor.
Everyday I get a letter from there saying that,
Her gün oradan bir mektup alıyorum,
“I’ve got Realization, I’ve got Realization,”
"Aydınlanmamı aldım, aydınlanmamı aldım" diyorlar
and it’s a very good way because you see they are writing about what is happening to this.
ve bu çok iyi bir şey çünkü olan biteni yazıyorlar.
So we have in writing, everything.
Yani her şeyi yazılı olarak elimizde var.
Now, this is very important is to go down there.
Şimdi, oraya gitmek çok önemli.
And, one day I’ll sit down with you and tell you
Ve bir gün sizinle oturup
what are the points to be covered with these people.
bu insanlarla konuşulması gereken noktaları anlatacağım.
They can’t believe it! They can’t believe it!
İnanamıyorlar, inanamıyorlar!
They are so brain-washed, they can’t just believe it.
Beyinleri o kadar yıkanmış ki, inanamıyorlar…
And they said, you see all the head is divided into sixteen parts, I tell you.
Ve dediler ki, görüyorsun, tüm kafa on altı parçaya bölünmüş. Size söylüyorum…
Horrible Agnya and they don’t want to believe it!
Agnya korkunç ve onlar buna inanmak istemiyorlar!
They said, “No it is doing good to us, it has done good to so many people,” and this and that.
Dediler ki, "Hayır, bu bize iyi geliyor, pek çok insana iyi geldi" ve bunun gibi şeyler.
I really, I can’t imagine!
Gerçekten, hayal bile edemiyorum!
But I said there is somebody like this will come and talk to you.
Ama Ben böyle biri gelip sizinle konuşacak, dedim.
They have taken your name, but I wish I had not given the name,
Adınızı aldılar ama keşke isim vermeseydim
because then they will ring up the main head
çünkü o zaman ana merkeze telefon edecekler
and there they might tell them that some (brain wave?).
ve orada onlara bazı (beyin?) söyleyecekler.
But in any case you must go and see this man.
Ama her halükarda bu adamı görmeye gitmelisin.
And then we got two other TM people there, who came to the program,
Sonra programa gelen iki TM'li daha vardı,
of whom Thomas was rather worried, because he was also in TM.
Thomas onlardan oldukça endişeliydi çünkü o da TM'deydi.
But when these two people came in, they told Me that he is a devil incarnate.
Ama bu iki kişi geldiğinde, Bana onun şeytanın vücut bulmuş hali olduğunu söylediler.
I said all right.
Ben, “Tamam” dedim.
So, there it started working out.
Böylece işler yoluna girmeye başladı.
You see then, Thomas got back his confidence also.
Sonra Thomas da güvenini geri kazandı.
So, the whole thing turned out very well.
Böylece her şey çok iyi sonuçlandı.
I think so, there was something.
Bence, bir şey vardı.
[Sahaja yogi talking: blue suits and red tie and…]
Sahaja Yogi konuşuyor: mavi takım elbise ve kırmızı kravat ve…
[NOT CLEAR]
[Net değil]
Blue suit was not there, but something he was little elegantly
Shri Mataji: Mavi takım elbise yoktu
dressed I should say,
ama biraz şık giyinmişti diyebilirim,
quite nicely dressed.
oldukça güzel giyinmişti.
But not exactly blue suits, but elegantly dressed people.
Ama tam olarak mavi takım elbise değil ama şık giyinmiş insanlar.
May be they might be Initiator for [NOT CLEAR]
Belki de [anlaşılmıyor] için başlangıç olabilirlerdi
but they said that he was the incarnation of devil.
ama onun şeytanın vücut bulmuş hali olduğunu söylediler.
They had no doubts.
Hiç şüpheleri yoktu.
So, this is what, so now you have to work it out.
Yani, şimdi bunu çözmeniz gerekiyor.
Now Spain people, out of only their phone numbers,
Şimdi İspanyollar, sadece telefon numaralarından
I will get their addresses.
adreslerini alacağım.
And Portugal.
Ve Portekiz.
All these things are to be looked after.
Bütün bu şeyler halledilmeli.
Portugal, Spain, France, Nice.
Portekiz, İspanya, Fransa, Nice.
Nice, we’ve got a very good center in Nice.
Nice, Nice'te çok iyi bir merkezimiz var.
But now, I think Marie is looking after,
Ama şimdi sanırım Marie ilgileniyor.
Marie has been really spending lot of money, she did a lot.
Marie gerçekten çok para harcadı, çok şey yaptı.
She did a lot, I must say.
Çok şey yaptı, söylemeliyim.
And, she is going to look after Nice.
Ve o Nice'e bakacak.
But still you should find out about it, what’s happening.
Ama yine de neler olduğunu öğrenmelisin.
So, we’ve got Portugal, then we’ve got Spain, Madrid,
Portekiz var, sonra İspanya, Madrid
then we’ve got Nice.
sonra Nice var.
And the addresses of all these people should be brought in.
Ve tüm bu insanların adresleri getirilmeli.
Today I’ll give you the addresses of California people.
Bugün size Kaliforniya'daki insanların adreslerini vereceğim.
Addresses of California is coming.
Kaliforniya'daki adresler geliyor.
So, Pradhan may be coming here.
Yani, Pradhan buraya gelebilir.
Then what else?
Sonra başka ne var?
Then we’ve got Paris, Lille.
Sonra Paris, Lille var.
Write it down all these places: Lille, Paris.
Tüm bu yerleri yazın: Lille, Paris.
Then, I went to Geneva, then Lausanne,
Sonra, Ben Cenevre'ye gittim sonra Lozan'a
then where did I go next to that? Zurich, Bern.
sonra oradan nereye gittim? Zürih, Bern.
Bern, Bern, Zurich and then Basel. Basel.
Bern, Bern, Zürih ve sonra Basel. Basel.
And then to this Freiburg.
Ve sonra bu Freiburg'a.
Freiburg, where our Rustom has done some job.
Freiburg, bizim Rustom'un iş yaptığı bir yer.
How are you? How is Mr.(?)
Nasılsınız Bay (?)
I don’t see him at all.
Onu hiç görmüyorum.
[Sahaja Yogi talking]
[Sahaja Yogi konuşuyor]
He is all right now?
O, şimdi iyi mi?
Upset?
Üzgün mü?
So then, what did I say?
Peki, Ben ne demiştim?
Then Bonn, Freiburg, then Bonn.
Sonra Bonn, Freiburg, sonra Bonn.
But you have to immediately write to Thomas,
Ama hemen Thomas'a yazıp,
find out from him what is he doing about it.
bu konuda ne yaptığını öğrenmelisin.
He wants somebody to go to Bonn, Freiburg.
Bonn'a, Freiburg'a birinin gitmesini istiyor.
So we have to arrange all these things, you see.
Yani tüm bunları ayarlamamız gerekiyor, görüyor musun?
There is one lady who is going to Nigeria form there.
Oradan Nijerya'ya gidecek bir bayan var.
She might work out it.
Belki o halledebilir.
So, get the list of people. All the list of these people and their addresses.
Yani, insanların listesini al. Tüm bu insanların listesini ve adreslerini.
Portugal, I don’t know if you have written to them, Portugal people.
Portekiz, onlara yazdın mı bilmiyorum, Portekizlilere.
What have you?
Ne var elinde?
[Sahaja Yogini talking]
[Sahaja Yogini konuşuyor]
But you wrote?
Ama yazdın mı?
They sent a letter to this girl.
Bu kıza bir mektup gönderdiler.
They have sent her a letter.
Ona bir mektup gönderdiler.
So better, write to her also so that form a complete circuit with them.
O yüzden, onlarla tam bir çevrim oluşturmak için ona da yazmak daha iyi olur.
So, this is the she is unhappy about something is to be put on the other side I think .
Yani, onun bir şeyden memnun olmadığı bu konu, Bence diğer tarafa konulmalı.
She is on one side she has been too much.
O bir tarafta, çok fazla kaldı.
Little move her to this side.
Onu bu tarafa biraz kaydırın.
So, now for England.
Şimdi İngiltere'ye gelelim.
Our great poet Blake has already…
Büyük şairimiz Blake zaten…
Did you read that Blake’s thing?
Blake'in yazdıklarını okudunuz mu?
Wonderful! Just imagine!
Harika! Düşünsene!
What a prophecy!
Ne kehanet ama!
So correct – and foundation so laid.
Çok doğru ve temeli atılmış.
See actually, he is seeing, just imagine how great they are in the laws of divine!
Aslında, o görüyor… Düşünsene, ilahi kanunlarda ne kadar büyükler!
You see that he prophesized, but for other people,
Onun kehanet ettiğini görüyorsun. Ama diğer insanlar...
you people don’t understand the value of all these things that you’re doing.
Sizler, yaptığınız tüm bu şeylerin değerini anlamıyorsunuz.
And we should see the profoundness of the whole thing –
Ve biz bütünün derinliğini görmeliyiz.
how profound it is, how we are handling the whole situation ourselves,
Ne kadar derin olduğunu, bütün durumu kendimiz nasıl idare ettiğimizi…
We are taking it still in a stride I think.
Bence biz bunu hala sakinlikle karşılıyoruz.
Imagine him to write all these things and all the prophecies he has made,
Onun bütün bunları yazdığını hayal edin ve yaptığı tüm kehanetleri yazdığını hayal edin…
now at least that will give I think some boost to London Sahaja Yogis.
En azından bu, Londra Sahaja Yogileri'ne biraz destek verecektir. Nasıl?
How? That they will realize their importance
Kendi önemlerini ve neyin önemli olduğunu anlayacaklar.
and that what important, I mean Jerusalem means the pilgrimages.
Demek istediğim Kudüs hac anlamına gelir. Bu, Kudüs'ün şimdi
from there to here.
oradan buraya taşınacağı anlamına gelir.
So what a great thing!
Ne harika bir şey!
Great prophet. He was a prophet.
Harika bir peygamber. O, bir peygamberdi.
You see, I picked him out.
Gördün mü, onu Ben seçtim.
Gavin, you remember? I went to see all his works.
Gavin, hatırlıyor musun? Tüm eserlerini görmeye gittim.
I mean, I picked him out. I didn’t know all this that he has done it.
Yani, onu Ben seçtim. Onun tüm bunları yaptığını bilmiyordum.
I didn’t know about this poem also this Jerusalem one.
Bu şiiri ve Kudüs şiirini de bilmiyordum.
And I think Warren has given Me one book but I read a little bit here and there not much.
Sanırım Warren Bana bir kitap vermişti ama biraz okudum ama çok fazla değil.
But I’m now going to read all that.
Ama şimdi hepsini okuyacağım.
Look at him. What a poet you had.
Ona bakın. Ne kadar büyük bir şairiniz varmış.
Prophet, a real prophet he was.
Peygamber, gerçek bir peygamberdi.
What a prophecy!
Ne kadar büyük bir kehanet!
So precise. So precise, imagine!
Çok kesin. Çok net, düşünün!
And beautifully described! Really beautifully described.
Ve çok güzel tanımlanmış. Gerçekten çok güzel tanımlanmış.
This is, who has done this?
Bu, bunu kim yaptı?
Jeremy has found out, is it?
Jeremy buldu, değil mi?
Sahaja yogi talking: Jeremy and then .[NOT CLEAR] and then Jeremy found this thing.
Sahaja Yogi: Jeremy ve sonra [net değil] ve sonra Jeremy bunu buldu.
Shri Mataji: One has to go into his works to find out what he has prophesized more.
Shri Mataji: Onun eserlerine bakmak gerekir, daha fazla ne kehanetlerde bulunduğunu öğrenmek için.
Sahaja Yogi: He got the whole, complete and also he got the complete work…
Sahaja Yogi: Her şeyi bütünüyle aldı; işi de eksiksiz şekilde tamamladı.
Shri Mataji: Great!
Shri Mataji: Harika!
Jerusalem.
Kudüs.
All right. So now for Jerusalem, what is to be done?
Pekâlâ. Peki, şimdi Kudüs için ne yapılmalı?
That we have to find out.
Bunu bulmamız gerekiyor.
That is to be little bit worked out in various methods, you see?
Bunun üzerinde çeşitli yöntemlerle biraz çalışılmalı, görüyor musunuz?
Gregoire has certain ideas.
Gregoire'ın bazı fikirleri var.
He said that we should materially improve ourselves first of all.
Öncelikle maddi olarak kendimizi geliştirmemiz gerektiğini söyledi.
Little bit. For presentation it’s important he said that.
Biraz. Sunum için bunun önemli olduğunu söyledi.
Gregoire, you see, he is very practical.
Gregoire, görüyorsunuz, çok pratik biridir.
He said, the presentation should be, if not blue suits
Sunumda, mavi takım elbise olmasa da
at least there should be some proper English suits, that should be worn
en azından uygun İngiliz takım elbiseleri giyilmesi gerektiğini söyledi.
because an Englishman like a hippy won’t be accepted anywhere.
Çünkü hippi gibi giyinen bir İngiliz hiçbir yerde kabul edilmez.
An Englishman to be dressed up properly is important.
Bir İngiliz'in uygun giyinmesi önemlidir.
So, that is something you find out what thing proper is.
Yani, neyin uygun olduğunu bulmanız gerekiyor.
But need not be absolutely one-color stuff but everybody should try to.
Ama mutlaka tek renk giyinmek gerekmez.
For presentation, when you go to a, say, a meeting or something,
Ama herkes bunu denemelidir. Sunum için, bir toplantıya örneğin bir toplantıya ya da başka bir yere
it should appear that it belonged to old, old style English traditional person.
gittiğinizde, eski eski tarz İngiliz geleneksel bir kişiye aitmiş gibi görünmelidir.
See, so people take you seriously,
Böylece insanlar sizi ciddiye alırlar,
which was Gregoire’s very good idea because for all these functions,
bu Gregoire'ın çok iyi bir fikriydi çünkü tüm bu etkinlikler için
he told all the people in Switzerland that they must dressup properly.
İsviçre'deki tüm insanlara düzgün giyinmeleri gerektiğini söyledi.
And then how to behave in a program and all that, he is very particular you see?
Ve sonra bir programda nasıl davranılacağı ve tüm bunlar, o çok titizdir, anlıyor musunuz?
For a newcomer, as he said to Me that for a newcomer,
Yeni gelenler için, Bana söylediği gibi, yeni gelenler için
what matters is your outside.
önemli olan sizin dış görünüşünüzdür.
They don’t know about your inside and how you behave and all that.
İçinizi, nasıl davrandığınızı ve tüm bunları bilmezler.
He said that, “Mother you make a
O, "Anne, bunun için
little outline for that and discuss with all the London people also.”
küçük bir taslak hazırlayın ve Londra'daki tüm insanlarla da tartışın" dedi.
How to work out the outside behavior of Sahaja Yogis
Sahaja Yogiler’in bir toplantıya gittiklerinde veya
when they go to a meeting or hold a meeting or work it out in a way.
bir toplantı düzenlediklerinde dış görünüşlerini nasıl düzenleyecekleri veya hangi şekilde halledeceklerini de…
Because it should look like one group and working out together.
Çünkü tek bir grup gibi görünmeli ve birlikte çalışmalılar.
One group is the main point is, you see?
Tek bir grup olması esas nokta, anlıyor musunuz?
And everybody should support each other in the presence of others.
Ve herkes diğerlerinin huzurunda birbirini desteklemeli.
See otherwise it looks
Aksi takdirde,
as if some blind people are trying to lead other blind.
sanki bazı körler diğer körleri yönlendirmeye çalışıyor gibi görünür.
It should appear that you people have achieved something
Sanki sizin bir şeyler başardığınız ve
and that you are all in one tune with each other
hepinizin birbirinizle uyum içinde olduğunuz,
or there is no quarrel between you and there is no indignity.
aranızda hiçbir çekişme bulunmadığı ve hiçbir saygısızlık olmadığı izlenimi vermeli.
Because if others, when they see you in this manner,
Çünkü diğerleri sizi bu şekilde gördüklerinde
they get frightened and they run away.
korkar ve kaçarlar.
So, he said that for that I have to make some outline,
Bu yüzden, bunun için
but I would like to have suggestions from you people and also on top of that,
bir taslak hazırlamam gerektiğini söyledi, ama sizlerden öneriler almak istiyorum
I hope you’ll make it ready by this week.
ve ayrıca,umarım bu hafta sonuna kadar hazırlarsınız.
All of you to give Me suggestions as to what sort of things we should have,
Hepiniz Bana insanlara sunabileceğimiz,
which will look presentable to people.
ne tür şeyler olması gerektiği konusunda önerilerde bulunun.
Like you see, they expect something of an Englishman
Gördüğünüz gibi, onlar bir İngilizden bir şeyler bekliyorlar
and if that is not there, then they tell, “These are some of the craps,” you see.
ve eğer bu olmazsa, "Bunlar saçmalık" derler.
So, Gregoire’s idea was correct that they should appear in this way
Yani Gregoire'in fikri doğruydu, bu şekilde görünmeleri gerekiyor.
and I think you should think over it. What should be done for.
Ve Bence bunu düşünmelisiniz. Ne yapılmalı?
And secondly, we have to find out, see the places where I visited
İkinci olarak, ziyaret ettiğim yerleri bulmamız
and try to allocate places to every Sahaja yogi,
ve bu yerleri görmek isteyen her Sahaja Yogi'ye
who would like to look at those places.
kalacak yerler ayarlamaya çalışmalıyız.
Now what happens to people who come and go away?
Şimdi, gelip giden insanlara ne oluyor?
What is the reason? You should find out. Go and talk to them.
Nedeni nedir? Bunu bulmalısınız. Gidip onlarla konuşun.
You must make a study of that.
Bunun üzerine bir araştırma yapmalısınız.
Why do they come to Sahaja Yoga and then disappear?
Neden Sahaja Yoga'ya geliyorlar ve sonra ortadan kayboluyorlar?
One of the reasons, as these people discussed was this, that, people are very naive.
Bu insanların tartıştığı nedenlerden biri,  insanların çok naif olmasıydı.
They don’t know what to expect.
Ne bekleyeceklerini bilmiyorlar.
So, Don’s book is also after realization, you see?
Yani, Don'un kitabı da aydınlanmadan sonra, anlıyor musunuz?
There should be a small introduction of Sahaja Yoga
Onlara göre Sahaja Yoga'nın küçük bir tanıtımı olmalı,
according to them
Onlara göre...
a small little introduction to Sahaja Yoga, what to expect, what to find.
Sahaja Yoga'ya küçük bir giriş, ne bekleyecekler, ne bulacaklar…
I think, one of My speeches is there which I gave you.
Sanırım, size verdiğim konuşmalarımdan biri orada.
We can sit down and chart out an introduction to Sahaja Yoga.
Oturup Sahaja Yoga'ya bir giriş hazırlayabiliriz.
What are we to expect, you see?
Ne bekleyeceğiz, anlıyor musunuz?
And a very direct thing should be there.
Ve çok doğrudan bir şey olmalı.
And, I mean for advertising, say for example you want to have a meeting somewhere,
Ve reklam için demek istiyorum... Örneğin bir yerde toplantı yapmak istiyorsanız,
you can even have pamphlets, you can even distribute and things that people can come
broşürler bile hazırlayabilirsiniz, dağıtabilirsiniz ve insanlar gelebilir
and intensively we should work out in every place.
ve her yerde yoğun bir şekilde çalışmalıyız.
Then it will grow faster.
O zaman daha hızlı büyüyecektir.
Pune is doing very good work, Pune. Tremendous.
Pune, çok iyi iş çıkarıyor. Pune... Muhteşem.
Apart from that, Bombay is doing very well.
Bunun dışında, Bombay de çok iyi gidiyor.
Rajesh was saying it is going very well in Maharashtra.
Rajesh, Maharashtra'da çok iyi gittiğini söylüyordu.
But the only difference between Maharashtra and other places is this:
Ama Maharashtra ile diğer yerler arasındaki tek fark şudur:
that they know about it beforehand.
Onlar bunu önceden biliyorlar.
They know Kundalini, they know what to expect, you see.
Kundalini'yi biliyorlar, ne bekleyeceklerini biliyorlar, anlıyor musunuz?
This is what is missing.
Eksik olan şey budur.
So if you can give it in writing, what to expect out of Self Realization, and very directly –
Yani, yazıyla verebilirseniz aydınlanmadan ne beklemeleri gerektiğini ve çok doğrudan noktaları yazabilirseniz...
the points.
Öncelikle ne beklemeleri gerektiğini...
First what to expect, what is Self Realization? What is Self?
Aydınlanma nedir, benlik nedir?
Very, very directly, you see, absolutely.
Çok, çok doğrudan, anlarsınız ya, tamamen açık bir şekilde.
So, that anybody who wants to read can see that.
Böylece okumak isteyen herkes görebilir.
And then he should see that what to expect and all.
Ve sonra ne beklemesi gerektiğini ve her şeyi görmelidir.
If we can prepare something like that,
Böyle bir şey hazırlayabilirsek,
then you prepare a sort of a, what you call a framework
o zaman bir tür, sizin deyiminizle bir çerçeve hazırlarsınız
and then we can fill it up.
ve sonra onu doldurabiliriz.
But should not be complicated, simple and very direct.
Ama karmaşık olmamalı, basit ve çok doğrudan olmalı.
Because even Don’s book is after Realization.
Çünkü Don'un kitabı bile aydınlanmadan sonra.
Before Realization, that book is bit too much.
Adyınlamadan öncesi için, o kitap biraz fazla.
We can do it in small, very small way.
Bunu küçük, çok küçük bir şekilde yapabiliriz.
There is no need to question and answer sort of thing we can do it very direct.
Soru-cevap gibi bir şeye gerek yok. Bunu çok doğrudan yapabiliriz.
Now, after Realization, people go away, you see.
Şimdi, aydınlanmadan sonra, insanlar gidiyor, görüyorsunuz.
Now for that also we have to understand why.
Şimdi bunun için de nedenini anlamamız gerekiyor.
Why people go and what should we do to stop them?
İnsanlar neden gidiyor ve onları durdurmak için ne yapmalıyız?
Some of them whom I talked to, you see,
Konuştuğum bazıları, görüyorsunuz,
why they went away is that some say there is no love between Sahaja Yogis.
neden gittiklerini söylüyorlar: Sahaja Yogiler arasında sevgi yok, diyorlar.
This is a very important point.
Bu çok önemli bir nokta.
They do not talk to each other with love.
Birbirleriyle sevgiyle konuşmuyorlar.
You see this is the fellow from Rajneesh, he was,
Görüyorsunuz, bu Rajneesh'ten gelen birisi...
and he said in Rajneesh there is lot of love.
O kişi, ''Rajneesh'te çok sevgi var.'' diyordu.
Well, you see it is filth, you know there, but doesn’t matter.
Orası pislik dolu, biliyorsunuz ama önemli değil.
To him outsider he sees everybody, you see, very friendly and nice and this and that.
Dışarıdan bakan biri olarak, herkesin çok dost canlısı, nazik ve falan filan olduğunu görüyor.
So,
Bu yüzden, bu tür bir soğukluk ve kibir
the kind of dryness and arrogance or we can say fighting and all that nonsense should be avoided.
ya da kavga ve tüm bu saçmalıklar kaçınılmalıdır.
So, all this we have to chart it out, but this is one of the reasons.
Tüm bunları planlamalıyız ama bu nedenlerden biri.
Secondly, they said that some of the Sahaja Yogis talk
İkincisi, bazı Sahaja Yogilerin
in such a manner as if they are great, you see.
sanki kendileri harikaymış gibi konuştuklarını söylediler.
They have achieved a lot and very egoistically they talk.
Çok şey başarmışlar ve çok egoistçe konuşuyorlar.
And that repels people.
Ve bu insanları uzaklaştırıyor.
They should talk in a softer way.
Daha yumuşak bir şekilde konuşmalılar.
That might be hinting at Gregoire, maybe, I don’t know.
Bu Gregoire'ı ima ediyor olabilir belki, bilmiyorum.
But I must say Gregoire’s shouting helps other way around.
Ama Gregoire'ın bağırmasının tam tersi bir etki yarattığını söylemeliyim.
I mean many people become very alert.
Yani birçok insan çok uyanık hale geliyor.
But his style is different you know. So everybody should not take to the same style.
Ama onun tarzı farklı, biliyorsunuz. Yani herkes aynı tarzı benimsememeli.
You can have different styles of approaching people.
İnsanlara yaklaşmak için farklı tarzlar olabilir.
It’s like Gavin and Gregoire both go hand-in-hand very well.
Gavin ve Gregoire gibi, ikisi de çok iyi bir uyum içindeler.
I mean if they both of them approach somebody,
Yani ikisi birine yaklaşırsa,
then the left and right both are put together.
sol ve sağ bir araya gelir.
Such combinations should be found out.
Bu tür kombinasyonlar bulunmalıdır.
You see where, the great thing is the friendship of Sahaja Yogis, you see.
Görüyorsunuz, harika olan şey  Sahaja Yogilerin dostluğudur.
The great friendship must be developed.
Büyük bir dostluk geliştirilmelidir.
That friendship I don’t know, should be like,
Bu dostluk, bilmiyorum,
Ram said that Pradhan is coming everybody felt very happy, you see.
Ram'ın Pradhan'ın geleceğini söylediğinde herkesin çok mutlu olduğu gibi olmalı.
Why? After all Pradhan is such an old man, 75-year old man coming here.
Neden? Sonuçta Pradhan yetmişbeş yaşında yaşlı bir adam.
But you feel so close to him, why?
Ama ona çok yakın hissediyorsunuz.  Neden?
Because you are born of the same Mother
Çünkü aynı Anne'den doğdunuz
and you are doing such a tremendous work
ve çok büyük bir iş yapıyorsunuz
and all these fellow feelings should come like a soldier fights
ve tüm bu dostluk duyguları, bir askerin
with [INAUDIBLE] others are also fighting the same way.
[anlaşılmıyor] ile savaşması gibi olmalı… Diğerleri de aynı şekilde savaşıyor.
But that is not there. You see it is more artificial.
Ama bu yok. Gördüğünüz gibi, daha yapay.
Sort of… I think that is what is… huh?
Bir nevi… Bence durum bu, değil mi?
Sahaja Yogi : Everyone’s attention is on very petty things all the time.
Sahaja Yogi: Herkesin dikkati her zaman çok önemsiz şeylerde.
Shri Mataji : I think so.
Shri Mataji: Bence de öyle.
Sahaja Yogi : There is not sort of enthusiasm and fire.
Sahaja Yogi: Bir tür coşku ve ateş yok.
Sort of, you know, energy [NOT CLEAR] It’s all whose turn is it to do this and I mean.
Bir tür, bilirsiniz, enerji [net değil] Bu işi kimin yapma sırası var, demek istediğim.
Shri Mataji: That, that should be stopped completely.
Shri Mataji: Bu, bu tamamen durdurulmalı.
That’s what I was saying.
Ben de bunu söylüyordum.
Why not get a maid servant for the Ashram?
Neden aşram için bir hizmetçi tutmuyorsunuz?
Better get a maid and pay herthan to worry about it.
Endişelenmektense bir hizmetçi tutup ona para ödeyin.
This is something that will pull you down so much.
Bu sizi çok aşağı çekecek bir şey,
I tell you so much. Hopeless.
çok fazla, size çok söylüyorum, çok fazla... Umutsuz...
Sahaja Yogi: Also I think there is a tendency to become a kind of hypochondriac, Mother.
Sahaja Yogi: Ayrıca bence bir tür hastalık hastası olma eğilimi var, Anne.
People become obsessed with their catches, you know, and they sit there
İnsanlar catchlerine takıntılı hale geliyorlar, bilirsiniz,
and just worrying about what catch they have got and all this, and they won’t do anything
oturup catchlerini ve tüm bunları düşünüp duruyorlar
for Sahaja yoga, you know. They just worry about themselves all the time.
ve Sahaja Yoga için hiçbir şey yapmıyorlar, bilirsiniz. Sadece her zaman kendileri için endişeleniyorlar.
Shri Mataji: See?
Shri Mataji: Gördünüz mü…
Now, for this I’ve told Harry that
Bunun için Harry'ye
you should not worry – now leave your hand, just sit, still I will look after it.
endişelenmemesi gerektiğini söyledim. Şimdi elini bırak, sadece otur. Ben hallederim.
You should not worry about your catches at all.
Catchlerin için hiç endişelenmemelisin.
The more you worry, the more the, they will be there.
Ne kadar endişelenirseniz, o kadar çok olurlar.
Now for example, you are very subtle.
Şimdi, örneğin, siz çok sübtilsiniz.
Gavin knows this point very well.
Gavin bu noktayı çok iyi bilir.
As you were subtler and they were subtler also. Very clever.
Siz daha sübtildiniz ve onlar da daha sübtildi. Çok zekiler. Beni rahatsız etmek için
They would like to come in the program to disturb Me.
programa gelmek isterler.
I’ll give one of the examples.
Size bir örnek vereceğim.
That in the program, they’ll come just to give a feeling that you’re unwell.
Programa sadece, sizin iyi olmadığınız hissini vermek için gelirler.
You start behaving like that.
Siz de öyle davranmaya başlarsınız.
So the other people, who are there they say, see they are unwell why should we be here?
Orada bulunan diğer insanlar da,
Then they start clearing yourself out like that.
"Bakın, onlar iyi değil, biz neden burada olalım?" derler. Sonra kendilerini bu şekilde temizlemeye başlarlar.
See all these things go against good publicity.
Bütün bunlar iyi tanıtıma aykırıdır.
Then their attention is on your, ‘I’m catching here I’m catching there’.
Sonra dikkatleri size yönelir, "Burada cacth ediyorum, orada catch ediyorum."
The more you do that, the more they will be there.
Bunu ne kadar çok yaparsanız, o kadar çok orada olurlar.
It’s all not catching anywhere. They will run away.
Hiçbir yerde catch yok. Kaçacaklar.
See, they are there just to create a problem for Me and for Sahaja Yoga.
Bakın, onlar sadece Bana ve Sahaja Yoga'ya sorun çıkarmak için oradalar.
So, better tell your mind that, “You get out from here. We don’t want any help. Had enough of you.”
O yüzden, zihninize şunu söyleyin: "Buradan çıkın. Yardım istemiyoruz. Sizden bıktık."
If you do that it will work out.
Bunu yaparsanız, işe yarayacaktır.
Or you should, best thing is to say, ‘Surrender’.
Ya da en iyisi "teslim oluyorum" demektir.
Surrender is the only way.
Teslim olmak tek yoldur.
Anything comes, “I’ll surrender myself to Mother, finished.
Ne olursa olsun "kendimi Anne'ye teslim edıyorum" bitti.
All these things will go away. That’s the best way.
Bütün bunlar ortadan kalkacak. En iyi yol budur.
Then you start seeing [?] very clearly, which I’ve been talking to Harry.
O zaman çok net bir şekilde görmeye başlayacaksın, Harry'ye de bunu anlatmıştım.
That he would used to worry like, “Where should I put my attention?”
O da "Dikkatimi nereye vermeliyim?" diye endişelenirdi.
I said you just don’t worry just say, ‘I surrender everything to you Mother’. Finished.
Ben de ona "Endişelenme, sadece 'Her şeyi Size teslim ediyorum Anne' de" dedim. Bitti.
Don’t try to do anything. Don’t try to take out.
Hiçbir şey yapmaya çalışma. Çıkarmaya çalışma.
Just surrender. They’ll all run away.
Sadece teslim ol. Hepsi kaçacak.
Otherwise they will be there creating a nuisance out of you.
Aksi takdirde orada kalacaklar ve sana rahatsızlık verecekler.
You see the trouble is the whole society is individualistic, you see.
Sorun, tüm toplumun bireyci olmasıdır.
So to get out of that individualistic society into a real social being,
Bu bireyci toplumdan çıkıp gerçek bir sosyal varlık olmak için,
in the sense that it has to be a real Sahaja Yogi collective being,
yani gerçek bir Sahaja Yogi, kolektif varlık olmak için,
then one has to remember not to pay any attention to yourself.
kendine hiç dikkat etmemek gerektiğini hatırlamak gerekir.
What is so important? [NOT CLEAR] who am I?
Ne bu kadar önemli ki? [anlaşılmaz] Ben kimim?
Sahaja Yogi: This is what I’ve been saying on Friday night.. It tends to be that people come in
Sahaja Yogi: Cuma gecesi söylediğim şey buydu. İnsanlar geldiklerinde sadece kendilerini düşünürler,
and they just think about themselves and they work on themselves without going to someone and saying,
ve birine gidip  "Sana yardım edebilir miyim?, Senin için bunu yapabilir miyim?"
‘Can I help you? Can I do this for you?’
demeden kendileri üzerinde çalışırlar.
Shri Mataji: No, No. That is also another subtler work is that I’ll help you. I’ll do this for you.
Shri Mataji: Hayır, hayır. Bu da daha sübtil bir çalışma: ''Ben sana yardım edeceğim. Bunu senin için yapacağım.''
Because this is again the missionary part of it.
Çünkü bu da yine misyonerlik kısmıdır.
I must tell you because Christians should be aware of it.
Size bunu söylemeliyim çünkü Hıristiyanlar bunun farkında olmalı.
What these missionary business of helping you. Whom are you helping?
Size yardım etmeyi vaad eden misyonerlik faaliyeti nedir? Kime yardım ediyorsunuz?
You are helping yourself.
Kendinize yardım ediyorsunuz.
The more you are with others, the more you are enjoying yourself.
Başkalarıyla ne kadar çok birlikte olursanız, o kadar çok eğlenirsiniz.
Sahaja Yogi : Being collective.
Sahaja Yogi: Kolektif olmak.
Shri Mataji: Just be collective.
Shri Mataji: Sadece kolektif olun.
Just do it because you like it, you love it
Sadece bunu hoşlandığınız için, sevdiğiniz için yapın
and by which you are the winner not the other.
ve böylece kazanan siz olursunuz, başkası değil.
You are the ones who are going to gain not the others.
Kazanacak olan sizlersiniz,
The more you [you will do it?] the more you [will gain?]
başkaları değil.
But, [it’s becoming?] subtler and subtler.
Ne kadar çok [bunu yaparsanız],
Like one would say that I am doing it because I become more powerful.
o kadar çok [kazanırsınız].
What am I? Because after all ascent is the point, isn’t it?
Ama gittikçe daha da sübtil hale geliyor.
You
Mesela biri,
have to ascend.
Ben bunu yapıyorum çünkü daha güçlü oluyorum diyebilir.
How far you have ascended in Sahaja yoga, how far your vibrations are alright,
Ben neyim? Çünkü sonuçta asıl nokta yükseliş, değil mi? Yükselmek zorundasınız.
how far you have gone deeper is the main point.
Sahaja Yogada ne kadar yükseldiğiniz, vibrasyonlarınızın ne kadar iyi olduğu, sizin ne kadar derine indiğiniz asıl nokta budur.
And that can only be achieved, only be achieved through surrender, nothing else.
Ve bu sadece teslimiyetle, başka hiçbir şeyle değil, sadece teslimiyetle başarılabilir.
Nothing else. Before and after.
Başka hiçbir şeyle değil. Önce ve sonra.
Putting your attention, complete surrender.
Dikkatinizi verin, tamamen teslim olun.
That will work out.
Bu işe yarayacaktır.
That will absolutely neutralize all these things [UNCLEAR hypochondriac …?]
Bu, tüm bu şeyleri nötralize edecek [hastalık hastası].
just put all the troubles onto Me.
Tüm sorunları Bana bırakın.
Even to this point [INAUDIBLE] like he, Harry,
Bu noktaya kadar bile [duyulmayan]
I’ve been studying you people through him very well.
Onun gibi, Harry… Onun aracılığıyla sizi
That, just now I talked to
çok iyi inceliyorum.
Harry and I told him that how subtle it becomes that,
Biraz önce Harry ile konuştum ve ona bunun ne kadar sübtil bir şey olduğunu söyledim,
he’s a very nice person, good-hearted, everything.
o çok iyi bir insan, iyi kalpli, her şey.
But the bhooths are not.
Ama bhoothlar öyle değil.
So, today I talked to Maharaj, this fellow from Africa.
Bugün Maharaj ile konuştum, Afrika'dan gelen bu adamla.
And in his talk, I discovered, he said, I was talking about a doctor,
Onun konuşmasında, keşfettim ki, bir doktordan bahsediyordum
and he told Me a sentence, “Mother, he is judging you”.
ve bana bir cümle söyledi, "Anne, o Sizi yargılıyor."
And that’s how he got hot and I said, “That’s it.”
Ve bu yüzden sinirlendi ve Ben de "İşte bu" dedim.
Anything that judges Me is wrong, like, “She’s doing this because She loves us.”
Beni yargılayan her şey yanlıştır, mesela "O bunu bizi sevdiği için yapıyor."
Even this point. Who are you?
Bu nokta bile. Sen kimsin? Bunun arkasındaki sübtilliği,
You see the subtleness, the subtle point behind this.
bunun arkasındaki ince noktayı görüyor musunuz? Bunu ona söyledim.
Can you see it? That’s what I told him.
Hanumana bu noktada sinirleniyor.
See Hanumana gets angry on this point.
Hanumana, kesinlikle yüzde yüz...
Hanumana, absolutely hundred percent.
Sen kimsin?
Who are you?
Neden seni sevmeli?
And because She loves us that’s why you must accept what am I saying to you.
Ve bizi sevdiği için,
What’s that?
sana söylediklerimi kabul etmelisin. O ne?
Hello?
Merhaba?
Just open the door. Who else has come?
Kapıyı aç. Başka kim geldi?
[Sahaja Yogini talking]
[Sahaja Yogini konuşuyor]
Hello your friend is coming is it? Who is coming?
Merhaba, arkadaşın mı geliyor? Kim geliyor?
She is trying to talk to Me.
Benimle konuşmaya çalışıyor. Ona ilgi göstermediğimde hoşuna gitmiyor.
She doesn’t like when I don’t pay any attention to her.
Pekâlâ.
All right.
Merhaba.
Hello. How are you?
Nasılsın?
It is nice to see you. Sit down. Sit down.
Seni görmek güzel. Otur. Otur.
So, how it becomes subtler and subtler, one should see.
Peki, nasıl daha da sübtil hale geliyor, bunu görmek gerekir.
And one should face it.
Ve bununla yüzleşmek gerekir. Ve sübtil yollar söz konusu olduğunda, kıdemli Sahaja Yogiler ile bu şey arasında bir fark olduğunu öylemeliyim.
And when the subtle ways, I must say there is a difference between
Bunu görüyorsunuz. Bir anlayış var, var. Her şey Sahaja Yoga bakış açısıyla yapılmalıdır. Sahaja Yoga'ya yardım ediyor muyuz, etmiyor muyuz?
the senior Sahaja Yogis and this thing.
Bence olgunluk yaşla gelir. Önemli olan Sahaja Yoga olmalıdır.
You just see this. There is a understanding, there is.
Ve hatta siz…
Anything should be done from the Sahaja Yoga point of view.
Yani, mutlaka iş bulmanız gerektiğini söyledim.
Are we helping Sahaja Yoga or not.
Kazanmalısınız.
I think maturity comes with age.
Çalışmalısınız.
The concern should be Sahaja Yoga.
Tarzınızı ve
And even if you, I mean I said you must take up jobs.
diğer şeyleri geliştirmelisiniz.
You must earn. Have to work.
Bir şekilde ama
You have to improve your styles and things.
Sahaja Yoga için.
Somewhat, but for Sahaja Yoga.
Bu Sahaja Yoga için yapılmalıdır.
It’s to be done for Sahaja Yoga.
Amaç, bu değil.
That’s not the aim. Aim is Sahaja Yoga.
Amaç, Sahaja Yoga'dır.
That’s the main point is.
Ana nokta, budur.
That Sahaja Yoga should be placed as the highest thing
Sahaja Yoga en üstün şey olarak yerleştirilmelidir. Ancak o zaman işe yarayacaktır
and then only it will work out, because all these subtle things will disappear.
çünkü tüm bu sübtil şeyler ortadan kalkacaktır.
you.
Ve size fikirler ve şeyler verirler
And they come as [UNCLEAR], you see, and they will give you ideas and things
ve onu gözden kaybetmeye başlarsınız.
because you must know that you have been prophesized long time back.
Çünkü uzun zaman önce kehanet edildiğini bilmelisiniz.
And you are doing such a tremendous work.
Ve çok muazzam bir iş yapıyorsunuz.
It’s such a great work you are doing.
Yaptığınız iş çok yüce.
I wish you could realize it, because even that understanding is very subtle.
Keşke bunu anlayabilseniz çünkü bu anlayış bile çok sübtil.
Then all other things you just throw away.
O zaman diğer her şeyi bir kenara atarsınız.
That Sahaja Yoga itself is self-established and have this self-esteem thing.
Sahaja Yoga kendi kendine kurulmuştur ve bu öz saygı şeyine sahiptir.
It does not need from you.
Sizden bir şeye ihtiyacı yoktur.
Only thing by taking it up yourself, you improve in your status.
Sadece bunu kendiniz benimsediğinizde, siz kendi statünüzü geliştirirsiniz.
Like that. Now see you understand.
Aynen öyle. Şimdi anlıyorsunuz.
You’re doing no favor to Sahaja Yoga or to Mataji Nirmala Devi.
Sahaja Yoga'ya veya Mataji Nirmala Devi'ye bir iyilik yapmıyorsunuz.
You’re doing favor to yourself.
Kendinize bir iyilik yapıyorsunuz.
Now, this point is the point I tell you.
Şimdi, size söylediğim nokta budur.
All right? So you surrender.
Tamam mı? Öyleyse teslim olun.
Surrendering is the only way. There is no other way.
Teslim olmak tek yoldur. Başka bir yol yoktur.
And that’s why these problems can be solved now.
Ve bu yüzden bu sorunlar şimdi çözülebilir.
So how do we do it?
Peki bunu nasıl yapacağız?
May God bless you.
Tanrı sizi kutsasın.
Oh, God! Good, good, come along, come along.
Oh, Tanrım! Güzel, güzel, gelin, gelin.
How are you? Good.
Nasılsınız?
Who else is coming from Cambridge?
İyi.
Sahaja Yogi: I’m from Australia.
Cambridge'den başka kim geliyor? Sahaja Yogi: Ben Avustralya'danım.
Sahaja Yogi: [Unclear]. He stays in the ashram.
Sahaja Yogi: O, aşramda kalıyor.
Shri Mataji: Come along.
Shri Mataji: Gelin. John da gelecek.
John will be coming. Dalla [unsure] would come,
Dalla [anlaşılmıyor] gelecektir, eminim.
I’m sure.
Sahaja Yogi: [Anlaşılmıyor]
Shri Mataji: Not yet arrived.
Shri Mataji: Henüz gelmedi.
Sahaja Yogi: I know. [Unclear].
Sahaja Yogi: Biliyorum. [Anlaşılmıyor]
Shri Mataji: Hmm. How to do it?
Shri Mataji: Hmm. Nasıl yapmalı?
“By not doing it”, he said, “by surrender”.
"Yapmayarak" dedi, "teslim olarak".
Sahaja Yogi: I’ll miss Mother that; It will then have a tendency to seat and
Sahaja Yogi: Bunu kaçırdım Anne; o zaman oturma eğilimi olacak ve
there’ll be a big mess and there is no point in doing anything, because-
büyük bir karışıklık olacak
[Laughter]
ve hiçbir şey yapmanın anlamı kalmayacak, çünkü...
Shri Mataji: Then you do everything. You see, when you become dynamic.
Shri Mataji: O zaman her şeyi sen yaparsın. Görüyorsun,
If you are not becoming dynamic, that means you are a gone case.
dinamik olduğunda... Eğer dinamik olmuyorsan, bu senin durumunun umutsuz olduğu anlamına gelir.
This is the judgment point.
Bu yargılama noktasıdır. Sahaja Yogi: O zaman hepimiz kaybedilmiş vakalarız, Anne. Shri Mataji: Hayır. Şimdi bunu söyleyemezsin.
Sahaja Yogi: We are all gone cases here then, Mother.
Sahaja Yogi: Aslında ne yapmalıyız?
Shri Mataji: No. You can’t say that now.
Başka bir Sahaja Yogi: Olduğu gibi bırakalım.
Sahaja Yogi: In fact, what we should be doing?
Shri Mataji: Öyle mi düşünüyorsunuz? Ben öyle düşünmüyorum.
Another Sahaja Yogi: Let it be as it is.
Sizi her yerde övüyorum.
Shri Mataji: You think so? I don’t think so.
Tabii, bazen çaresiz kaldığım da oluyor.
I’ve been praising you people all over.
Bu ülkedeki insanların
Of course, sometimes I used to get frantic.
tek bir sorunu olduğunu
I must say the people in this country, have only one problem, is lethargy.
söylemeliyim, o da uyuşukluk.
I will say, get active also.
Ben de diyorum ki, biraz da aktif olun.
They can be only bathroom
Yapabildikleri tek şey banyo
cleaners.
temizlemek oluyor.
This is the problem.
Sorun bu.
So, the inactivity can be dangerous.
Yani, hareketsizlik tehlikeli olabilir.
But I’m saying of non-action.
Ama Ben eylemsizlikten bahsediyorum.
I’m not saying of inactivity,
Hareketsizlikten bahsetmiyorum.
where the feeling that, “I’m doing something” is not there.
"Ben bir şey yapıyorum" hissinin olmadığı durumdan bahsediyorum.
We have to be active, extremely active, but say, “I’m not doing it “. Surrendered.
Aktif olmalıyız, son derece aktif
If you are lethargic, then you are no good.
ama "Ben yapmıyorum" demeliyiz. Teslim olmalıyız.
Non-action is very different.
Eylemsizlik çok farklıdır.
Like the sun comes and gives you light. It just emits.
Güneşin gelip size ışık vermesi gibi.
It is non-action. It doesn’t say, “I’m doing it “.
Sadece yayar. Bu eylemsizliktir. "Ben yapıyorum" demez.
You see the difference between the two.
İkisi arasındaki farkı görüyorsunuz.
It should be clearly understood.
Bu açıkça anlaşılmalıdır.
Sahaja Yogi: Do you think, Mother, that sometimes there is a tendency
Sahaja Yogi: Anne, bazen
to feel that if you do something in an active way, that you may
aktif bir şekilde bir şey yaparsanız,
get a catch in the left or right heart. Then there’s a sense, there is a tendency then
sol veya sağ kalbinizde bir catch hissedersiniz diye bir eğilim olduğunu düşünüyor musunuz?
not to do anything, since we go closer of your – you that you might go catching or doing something.
Ondan sonra, Size yaklaşırken bir catch olabilir ya da yanlış bir şey yapabiliriz düşüncesiyle, hiçbir şey yapmamaya yönelme eğilimi ortaya çıkıyor.
Another Sahaja Yogi: It’s hypochondriac thing.
Başka bir Sahaja Yogi: Bu hastalık hastalığı bir şey.
Sahaja Yogi: And that’s the hypochondria.
Sahaja Yogi: Evet, bu hastalık hastalığı.
Another Sahaja Yogi: I’m catching on left heart, so I can’t do anything… the whole day.
Başka bir Sahaja Yogi: Sol kalbimde catch hissediyorum, bu yüzden bütün gün hiçbir şey yapamıyorum.
Shri Mataji: I mean, Sahaja Yoga is not for such cowards.
Shri Mataji: Demek istediğim, Sahaja Yoga bu tür korkaklar için değil.
They are useless, they better get out.
Onlar işe yaramazlar, çıksalar iyi olur.
You see, it’s meant for people who are real warriors, you see, we need soldiers.
Görüyorsunuz, bu gerçek savaşçılar için, askerlere ihtiyacımız var.
Sahaja Yogi : We must fight now. We got to get out and fight.
Sahaja Yogi: Şimdi savaşmalıyız. Dışarı çıkıp savaşmalıyız.
Shri Mataji: They will go out of circulation, don’t you worry, all such people, very soon.
Shri Mataji: Onlar döngüden çıkacaklar, endişelenme, tüm bu insanlar çok yakında…
So, those who are afraid of catching, they go out of circulation.
Yani, catch etmekten korkanlar,
Here
döngüden çıkacaklar.
we are not here to look after your chakras.
Biz burada senin çakralarına bakmak için bulunmuyoruz.
We are here to work for Sahaja Yoga.
Biz, Sahaja Yoga için çalışmak için buradayız.
When you start working for Sahaja Yoga, you are automatically cured and geared up.
Sahaja Yoga için çalışmaya başladığında, otomatik olarak iyileşir ve hazır hale gelirsin.
That’s what it is.
İşte böyle.
Sahaja Yogi: Donna said something very appropriate when we were talking. She said,
Sahaja Yogi: Donna konuşurken çok uygun bir şey söyledi.
“One just has to look at the little ones.”
"Sadece küçüklere bakmak yeter" dedi.
Shri Mataji: Yes.
Shri Mataji: Evet.
She is working for all of you left, right everywhere.
O; sol sağ, her yerde, hepiniz için çalışıyor.
[Shri Mataji is laughing]
Bu bir oyun.
That’s a game. That’s a game she’s playing.
Onun oynadığı bir oyun.
The game we are all in like you, smiling too.
Hepimizin içinde olduğu bir oyun, sizin gibi, gülümsüyor da.
Sahaja Yogi:
Sahaja Yogi: Şunu anlamalıyız ki,
This is what we must realize that they work very hard.
onlar çok sıkı çalışıyorlar.
Shri Mataji: That’s true! Extremely, extremely hard.
Shri Mataji: Bu doğru! Son derece, son derece sıkı…
And they scream and shout and everything.
Ve bağırıyorlar, çığlık atıyorlar ve her şeyi yapıyorlar.
Sahaja Yogi: Cause it is quite obvious that when someone comes in, who’s got a bad catch,
Sahaja Yogi: Çünkü birisi geldiğinde, kötü bir catch olduğunda,
because the working-out starts immediately because of things.
işler hemen başlıyor çünkü bazı şeyler oluyor.
Shri Mataji: What things?
Shri Mataji: Ne gibi şeyler?
Better you learn from them.
Onlardan öğrenmelisiniz.
I should be the one, who is catching the most.
En çok catch eden kişi
[Shri Mataji is laughing]
Ben olmalıyım.
Humm.
Hmm.
eight steps forward, four steps backwards.
sekiz adım ileri, dört adım geri.
Ten steps forward, eleven steps backwards.
On adım ileri, on bir adım geri.
And where do you reach? What is the speed?
Ve nereye varırsınız? Hız nedir?
That’s what England is.
İngiltere bu.
[Shri Mataji is laughing]
[Shri Mataji gülüyor]
But everybody of the whole is progressing.
Ama herkes ilerliyor.
No doubt, slow and steady. We’ll win the race.
Şüphesiz, yavaş ve istikrarlı. Yarışı kazanacağız.
Sahaja Yogi: I mean a wind of change came in the last week when this girl arrived from Australia.
Sahaja Yogi: Demek istediğim, geçen hafta Avustralya'dan gelen bu kızla birlikte bir değişim rüzgarı esti.
I mean it was really, someone I never met so positive and everything else like that.
Yani gerçekten, bu kadar pozitif ve her yönüyle böyle olan birisi ile daha önce hiç tanışmamıştım.
Shri Mataji: They are the children of convicts, you see? So.
Shri Mataji: Onlar negatif kişilerin çocukları, görüyor musun?
So fresh! Annick, there is another one. Her name was Annick.
Çok taze! Annick, bir tane daha var. Adı Annick'ti.
She met us in Orleans. She came all the way to meet Marie.
Orleans'ta bizimle tanıştı. Marie ile tanışmak için o kadar yolu geldi.
Ah, you were there.
Ah, sen de oradaydın.
She went round and took all the posters.
Etrafta dolaşıp tüm posterleri aldı.
You see Marie, as usual, brought up from England.
Marie, her zamanki gibi, İngiltere'den getirdi.
So, she said, “Mother, she didn’t tell me beforehand. She had put the
Anne, bana önceden haber vermedi, dedi.
advertisement in the paper. But, she didn’t find out when it was”.
Gazeteye ilan vermişti. Ama ne zaman yayınlanacağını öğrenememişti.
So, it was on the third day the advertisement stopped.
üçüncü gün ilanlar durdu.
And there were no advertisements for the two days before.
Ve önceki iki gün boyunca ilan yoktu.
So, this Annick said, “Doesn’t matter”.
Bu yüzden Annick, "Önemli değil" dedi.
She went and put posters everywhere eight days before.
Gidip sekiz gün önce her yere posterler astı.
Everybody put the posters.
Herkes posterleri astı.
And on the poster only, Annick got so many.
Ve sadece posterlerde, Annick çok fazla aldı.
And Marie said, “Mother, I’m still an intuit, I don’ know.
Marie, "Anne, ben hala sezgiselim, bilmiyorum.
This thing happened; the third day we got all a big [unclear] crowd.
Bu olay oldu; üçüncü gün hepimiz büyük bir [belirsiz] kalabalık toplandı.
But these people who came with the posters, stayed on for two days and really came up very well.
Ama posterlerle gelen bu insanlar iki gün kaldılar ve gerçekten çok iyiydiler.
And then, they started working it out.
Ve sonra, çalışmaya başladılar.
Now Paris is very well established.
Şimdi Paris çok iyi bir şekilde kuruldu.
But this is what it is and the way she, I mean, tremendous she was, isn’t it?
Ama durum bu ve onun yaptığı şey, yani, o muhteşemdi, değil mi?
Orleans, she did it very well. She is really tremendous.
Orleans, çok iyi yaptı. O gerçekten muhteşem.
To her, Sahaja Yoga is her life. Absolutely.
Onun için Sahaja Yoga onun hayatıdır. Kesinlikle.
Australians are going to show a way to you people, I think.
Avustralyalılar size bir yol gösterecekler, Bence.
The convicts are born here to pull us down everywhere, you go everywhere.
Negatif kişiler bizi her yerde aşağı çekmek için burada doğuyorlar, nereye giderseniz gidin.
You find those convicts, eh?
O negatif kişileri buluyorsunuz, değil mi?
Sahaja Yogi:
Sahaja Yogi: Bir değişim programına ihtiyacımız var.
We need an exchange scheme.
Oraya birkaç tane göndereceğiz. Burada bir anlamı yok.
[Shri Mataji is laughing]
Shri Mataji: Hayır,
Sahaja Yogi: We’ll send some over there. No sense up here.
Bence bu
[Shri Mataji is laughing]
en kötü zamanlarda
Shri Mataji: No, I think it is alcoholism, of the worst time.
görülen alkolizm.
Now in front of her house, we find five, six of them permanently circle.
Şimdi onun evinin önünde beş, altı tanesi sürekli dolaşıyor.
One of them is a lady.
İçlerinden biri bir kadın.
Early in the morning, they are all drinking.
Sabahın erken saatlerinde hepsi içiyorlar.
And by yesterday we were, me and this doctor who has come, we were going down.
Dün Ben ve gelen bu doktor aşağı iniyorduk.
One of them was standing with a bottle and was singing and going forward and backwards.
İçlerinden biri elinde bir şişeyle durmuş şarkı söylüyor ve ileri geri gidip geliyordu.
So this Indian doctor got a fright.
Bu Hintli doktor çok korktu.
He said, “Better go by another road, because he may just shoot off”.
"Başka bir yoldan gidelim, yoksa ateş edebilir" dedi.
I said, “So this is what it is”.
Ben de "Demek durum bu" dedim.
But Swiss people are very speedy, very speedy people.
Ama İsviçreli insanlar çok hızlı, çok hızlı  insanlar...
They are on the other side. They are so speedy.
Onlar diğer tarafta, çok hızlılar.
Means, you know, it’s like a low train which never reaches the point.
Yani, bilirsiniz, hiçbir yere varamayan yavaş bir tren gibi.
And the fast one which always misses the station, it is like that.
Ve her zaman istasyonu kaçıran hızlı tren gibi... Öyle bir şey.
I don’t know which one to travel.
Hangisiyle seyahat edeceğimi bilmiyorum.
Sahaja Yogi: [Unclear].
Sahaja Yogi: [Belirsiz].
That is the situation of the West is.
Shri Mataji: Batı'nın durumu bu.
So, when you realize all this, we must see and try to correct it.
Yani, tüm bunları fark ettiğinizde bunu görmeli ve düzeltmeye çalışmalıyız.
But only difference perhaps is that difference- difference I find in this,
Ama belki de tek fark, bu fark,
that they understand their mistakes. And-
onların hatalarını anladıklarıdır. Ve…
Sahaja Yogi: It’s really the German section, I think. They really.
Sahaja Yogi: Bence bu gerçekten Alman kesimi. Onlar gerçekten.
Shri Mataji: No, all of them. Swiss also.
Shri Mataji: Hayır, hepsi. İsviçreliler de.
They also, they all understand.
Onlar da, onların hepsi anlıyor.
They say, “Mother, we are very speedy, we have to bring down, put down my speedometer”. You see.
"Anne, biz çok hızlıyız, hızımızı düşürmeliyiz, hız göstergemizi indirmeliyiz" diyorlar. Anlıyor musunuz?
And this is what we people do not realize, that we are lethargic here.
Ve biz insanların fark etmediği şey, bizim burada uyuşuk olduğumuzdur.
The difference is, lethargic people they never realize
Fark şu ki, uyuşuk (tembel) insanlar bunu asla fark etmezler
because they don’t even have so much strength to think of that, that we are lethargic.
çünkü uyuşuk olduklarını düşünecek kadar bile enerjileri yoktur.
My husband’s place, Lucknow, is known for all kinds of lethargic people.
Kocamın memleketi olan Lucknow, her türden uyuşuk insanlarla ünlüdür.
So, they had a competition.
Bir yarışma düzenlediler.
They got all of them in a row and said, “Whosoever is the most
Hepsini sıraya dizip,
lethargic, the laziest, walk one step forward”.
"En uyuşuk, en tembel olan, bir adım öne çıksın" dediler.
So everybody walks one step forward.
Herkes bir adım öne çıktı.
But one was from England. He stayed back.
Ama biri İngiltere'dendi. O geride kaldı.
So the people asked him, “Why didn’t you step forward?”
İnsanlar ona "Neden öne çıkmadın?" diye sordular.
He said, “I don’t even want to do that”.
O da "Bunu bile yapmak istemiyorum" dedi.
[Laughter]
[Kahkahalar]
It’s true that was the laziest.
En tembel olanın o olduğu doğruydu.
So that should not do the case. All right?
Yani bu durum geçerli olmamalı. Tamam mı?
See the working is on still, the right side, right side, right side.
Çalışmanın hala devam ettiğini görün. Sağ taraf, sağ taraf, sağ taraf...
It’s all working, yes, yes, yes, yes, it’s going on all the time.
Her şey çalışıyor. Evet, evet, evet, evet... Sürekli devam ediyor.
Ah! It’s working. Poor things.
Ah! Çalışıyor. Zavallı şeyler.
I have seen my grandchildren also. Aradhana,
Torunlarımı da gördüm. Aradhana,
she was hardly three years or so, we had taken her to the airport.
üç yaşında falandı, onu havaalanına götürmüştük.
She said, “No, no”, like that. She was going on like that, you see.
"Hayır, hayır" dedi, öyle. Öyle devam ediyordu, görüyorsunuz.
So, Kalpana could not understand why she was so crazy, so fast.
Kalpana, onun neden bu kadar çılgın, bu kadar hızlı olduğunu anlayamadı.
[To other Sahaja Yogis] Hello, hello, hello!
Merhaba, merhaba, merhaba!
Here comes then another mister [a baby boy]. Is he sleeping?
İşte başka bir beyefendi geliyor. Uyuyor mu?
Sahaja Yogini: No, no. [Unclear] Kamala
Sahaja Yogini: Hayır, hayır. [Belirsiz]
Shri Mataji: Come along. Where will you sit new?
Shri Mataji: Gelin. Nereye oturacaksınız?
Sit here.
Buraya oturun.
How are you now? Better? All right, I’ll see.
Şimdi nasılsınız? Daha iyi misiniz? Tamam, bakayım.
Ah! This one has come. This one,
Ah! Bu geldi. Bu...
thing.
Tanrı seni kutsasın.
Shri Mataji [talking to baby]: What has happened? Hum?
Sıcak. O hepinizden catch alıyor. Sahaja Yogi: O, yardım istiyor.
How much they work, I tell you, really.
Shri Mataji: Ne kadar çok çalıştıklarını size söyleyeyim, gerçekten.
Yes, yes.
Evet, evet.
Hmm. Swadisthana.
Hmm. Swadisthana.
So, this is what we have to do now. We have covered these points.
Öyleyse, şimdi yapmamız gereken bu. Bu noktaları ele aldık.
Now about your travelling, when can you do it?
Şimdi seyahatinizle ilgili olarak, ne zaman yapabilirsiniz?
Sahaja Yogi: As soon as possible. I’ll write to her, if you want.
Sahaja Yogi: Mümkün olduğunca çabuk. İsterseniz ona yazarım.
Shri Mataji: Ask Thomas, first of all. Will you go via Germany?
Shri Mataji: Önce Thomas'a sorun. Almanya üzerinden mi gideceksiniz?
Sahaja Yogi: I think so.
Sahaja Yogi: Sanırım öyle.
Shri Mataji: All right.
Shri Mataji: Tamam.
Sahaja Yogi: The van, the combi is, you know that combi is, it takes very short time.
Sahaja Yogi: Minibüs, kombi, bilirsiniz… O kombi, çok kısa sürede gider.
Another Sahaja Yogi: Rolthar has sent a thousand pounds to get the van fixed up. So,
Başka bir Sahaja Yogi: Rolthar, minibüsü tamir ettirmek için bin pound gönderdi.
it can be used for Sahaja Yoga programs.
Böylece Sahaja Yoga programları için kullanılabilir.
Really? Very sweet of him.
Shri Mataji: Gerçekten mi? Çok nazik biri.
Sahaja Yogi: And if there’s myself in a company, and one other person lately who can go,
Sahaja Yogi: Ve eğer ben ve son zamanlarda gidebilecek başka bir kişi varsa,
then we can stay in the van and do the cooking and everything else in the van.
minibüste kalabilir ve minibüste yemek pişirme ve diğer her şeyi yapabiliriz.
Shri Mataji: Good idea. That’s a good idea.
Shri Mataji: İyi fikir. Bu iyi bir fikir.
Can it be fixed or not? Put it in.
Tamir edilebilir mi? Koyun.
Sahaja Yogi: Yes, it can be fixed.
Sahaja Yogi: Evet, ayarlanabilir.
Shri Mataji: So we should assign it to some proper. Find a-
Shri Mataji: Öyleyse bunu uygun birine atamalıyız. Birini bul…
Sahaja Yogi: Mark is organising.
Sahaja Yogi: Mark organize ediyor.
Sahaja Yogi: [Unclear] to find the keys so he can take it there.
Sahaja Yogi: Mark minibüs konusunda ne yapıyor?
You have to pay him some money or something?
Ona para falan ödemeniz gerekiyor mu?
Sahaja Yogi: Yes, indeed.
Sahaja Yogi: Evet, tabii ki.
I think we should send him the money.
Shri Mataji: Bence ona parayı göndermeliyiz.
Otherwise, he’s a nice fellow, but he’s a great friend of one, Sinhalese.
Aksi takdirde, o iyi bir adam ama Sinhalese'nin çok iyi bir arkadaşı.
And this Sinhalese fellow wants me to go to Siloe.
Ve bu Sinhalese denen adam Siloe'ye gitmemi istiyor.
He’s quite a nice person.
Oldukça iyi bir insan.
And he’s a great friend of Mr. Bard.
Ve Bay Bard'ın çok iyi bir arkadaşı.
And Bard has given a very funny picture about you.
Bard senin hakkında çok komik bir resim çizdi.
Sahaja Yogini: He’s very negative in general.
Sahaja Yogini: Genel olarak çok olumsuz biridir.
Shri Mataji: Hum?
Shri Mataji: Ha?
Sahaja Yogini: He’s a very happy bachelor [unsure]. [Unclear] Well, when he will.
Sahaja Yogini: Çok mutlu bir bekârdır [belirsiz]. Eh, ne zaman olursa.
Shri Mataji: I never met him. I never met Bard.
Shri Mataji: Onunla hiç tanışmadım. Bard ile hiç tanışmadım.
It was his friend who told me about it.
Bana bunu onun arkadaşı anlattı.
Sahaja Yogini: Yes. Well, from our end what happened was-
Sahaja Yogini: Evet. Eh, bizim tarafımızda olan şey buydu…
Shri Mataji: Hum?
Shri Mataji: Hmm?
Sahaja Yogini: Wendy was taking some things to sell, at this sort of junk shop.
Sahaja Yogini: Wendy, bir tür hurda dükkânında satmak için bazı şeyler alıyordu.
And Bard happened to be in the shop because he was a friend of the man who owned it.
Bard da dükkânda bulunuyordu çünkü dükkanın sahibinin arkadaşıydı…
And he started saying all sorts of very derogatory things.
Ve her türlü aşağılayıcı sözler söylemeye başladı.
Shri Mataji: Come here, just I can’t hear you.
Shri Mataji: Buraya gel, seni duyamıyorum.
Sahaja Yogini: Sorry. He-
Sahaja Yogini: Özür dilerim. O...
Shri Mataji: Where did she go?
Shri Mataji: Nereye gitti?
Sahaja Yogini: Well, just by, oh sorry,
Sahaja Yogini: Şey, sadece, oh özür dilerim, inanılmaz,
amazing, well coincidence if you like, Wendy took some old books and stuff of ours to sell.
tesadüf diyebiliriz, Wendy bizim eski kitaplarımızı ve eşyalarımızı satmak için götürdü.
And she happened to meet Bard in this sort of shop, second hand shop. And he happened to be a
Ve bu tür bir dükkânda, ikinci el dükkanında Bard ile karşılaştı.
friend of the person who owns it, that was why he was in there. And he said lots of very derogatory
O da dükkân sahibinin arkadaşıydı bu yüzden oradaydı. Ve çok aşağılayıcı şeyler söyledi.
things. And Wendy said, she said, “I don’t think he’s still in Sahaja Yoga “. And then she said,
Wendy, "Onun hala Sahaja Yoga'da olduğunu sanmıyorum" dedi.
“Oh he said some very bad things about Peter “. So I said, “Well, you know, maybe… “
Sonra da "Peter hakkında çok kötü şeyler söyledi" dedi. Ben de "Belki de…" dedim.
Shri Mataji: About Peter he said lots of things.
Shri Mataji: Peter hakkında birçok şey söyledi.
Sahaja Yogini: Yes.
Sahaja Yogini: Evet.
Shri Mataji: But about Me, he said, “Mataji is too simple. She can’t understand”.
Shri Mataji: Ama benim hakkımda, "Mataji, çok basit. Anlayamıyor." dedi.
Shri Mataji: It’s horrible things. Horrible things.
Shri Mataji: Korkunç şeyler. Korkunç şeyler.
Which I will tell him otherwise.
Ona başka türlü söyleyeceğim.
Sahaja Yogini: But the other strange thing that happened is that we haven’t heard anything
Sahaja Yogini: Ama olan diğer garip şey,
about him from the point of view of Sahaja Yoga. And last night he happened to ring up.
Sahaja Yoga açısından onun hakkında hiçbir şey duymamış olmamız. Ve dün gece tesadüfen aradı.
Now what happened was that, I think it was Anne on the phone and she didn’t know, you know,
Olan şey şuydu, sanırım telefonda Anne vardı ve o bilmiyordu,
the whole thing about Bard. And she said, “Yes, there’s a puja tomorrow at four o’clock”.
Bard ile ilgili olanları bilmiyordu. Ve dedi ki, "Evet, yarın saat dörtte bir puja var."
And he said, “Can I speak to Harry? ” So I said to Anne, because she was new to him, I said, stop,
Ve o dedi ki, "Harry ile konuşabilir miyim?" Ben de Anne'e -çünkü o onun için yeni biriydi- dedim ki,
stop, stop, stop, stop, stop, put a hand over the phone sort of thing. And I didn’t know if
dur, dur, dur, dur...  Elini telefonun üzerine koy gibi bir şey.
this was right, Mother, but I said that it was only an invited puja and that certain people,
Bunun doğru olup olmadığını bilmiyordum ama bunun sadece davetlilerin katılabileceği bir puja olduğunu ve
only people who had been invited should come. And it was only a small thing because I
sadece davet edilenlerin gelebileceğini söyledim. Bu sadece küçük bir şeydi çünkü birdenbire,
suddenly thought, you know, is there some negativity trying to sort of come in or? Anyway,
bilirsiniz, bir tür negativite mi girmeye çalışıyor diye düşündüm.
he’s probably coming to Caxton Hall because he said, “When is the next public meeting?”
Her neyse, muhtemelen Caxton Hall'a geliyor çünkü "Bir sonraki halka açık toplantı ne zaman?" dedi.
Shri Mataji: No, no, he clearly said that, “I do believe in Sahaja Yoga”.
Shri Mataji: Hayır, hayır, açıkça "Sahaja Yoga'ya inanıyorum" dedi.
You see, this fellow was all praised for him, he said this.
Görüyorsunuz, bu adam onun için övgü dolu sözler söyledi, bunu söyledi.
I said, “But he did pay some money. I believe what I heard is that electrical money and all that”.
Ben de "Ama biraz para ödedi. Duyduğuma göre elektrik parası ve benzeri şeylermiş.
And he said, “No, he’s not a man. If you tell
O da "Hayır, o öyle bir adam değil.
him he’ll pay. He’s a [unclear] formal man for money matters”.
Eğer söylerseniz öder. Para konusunda [belirsiz] resmi bir adamdır." dedi.
He said, “He is such a straightforward person, you can’t imagine and
"O kadar dürüst biridir ki, hayal bile edemezsiniz,
he’s a very fine person and most reliable”.
çok iyi biridir ve son derece güvenilirdir." dedi.
I mean, Sinhalese was all praised for him”.
Yani, Sinhalese onu çok övdü.
But he said, “He told about Peter, that Peter is a dangerous guy and all those things.
Ama dedi ki, "Peter hakkında, Peter'in tehlikeli bir adam olduğunu ve tüm bu tür şeyleri anlattı.
And that’s how he got out from there”.
Ve oradan bu şekilde kurtulduğunu söyledi.
And he said that, “Everybody will be in a
Ve "Herkes tehlike altında olacak" dedi,
jeopardy”, lots of things which I’ll tell you later.
daha sonra size anlatacağım birçok şey.
All right, whatever it is.
Tamam, her neyse.
[To the baby] Now, what’s happening? Why were you screaming so much?
[Bebeğe] Şimdi ne oluyor? Neden bu kadar çok bağırıyordun?
Hello? Hello?
Aaa... Hah... Merhaba?
All the time smiling and you are screaming for nothing at all.
Sürekli gülümsüyorsun ve hiçbir şey yokken bağırıyorsun.
You are also smiling now.
Şimdi de gülümsüyorsun.
Why were you screaming?
Neden bağırıyordun?
These people are troubling you a lot? Are they? Yes.
Bu insanlar seni çok rahatsız mı ediyor? Öyle mi? Evet.
So what do you do to them?
Peki, onlara ne yapıyorsun?
You scream at them, you shout at them, he?
Onlara bağırıyor musun,
Gavin?
Gavin? Sahaja Yogi: Evet
“Today at least have lunch with me”.
"Bugün en azından benimle öğle yemeği ye" dedi.
[Shri Mataji is laughing]
Shri Mataji: Şimdi uyandı.
Well, I don’t know. You see Bumble started off with eyes that colour.
Sahaja Yogini: Şey, bilmiyorum.
Shri Mataji: Yes, she’s got blue eyes. That’s a nice thing.
Shri Mataji: Evet, mavi gözleri var. Bu çok güzel.
Sahaja Yogini: They changed.
Sahaja Yogini: Değiştiler.
Shri Mataji [to the baby]: Yes!
Shri Mataji [bebeğe]: Evet!
Who had blue eyes in your family?
Ailenizde mavi gözlü kim vardı?
Sahaja Yogini: Well, nobody. I didn’t know either.
Sahaja Yogini: Hiç kimse. Ben de bilmiyordum.
Shri Mataji: She has blue eyes. Oh, you’re all right. Are they?
Shri Mataji: Mavi gözleri var. Oh, haklısın. Öyle mi?
Better, hold her a moment.
Daha iyi... Annene git...
So, this is what Bard has been doing, doesn’t matter.
Demek Bard bunu yapıyormuş, önemli değil.
But in any case, we should send him money, whatever it is.
Ama her halükarda, ona para göndermeliyiz, ne olursa olsun.
You should say that, “You just disappeared and I have to send the money to him “.
"Sen ortadan kayboldun ve ben ona para göndermek zorundayım" demelisin.
Then another thing is you have to
Bir başka şey de,
see to it that, you see, when all such things start, one should not talk.
tüm bu tür şeyler başladığında, kimse konuşmamalı.
Because, you see, whatever it is, money is different from Sahaja Yoga.
Çünkü, ne olursa olsun, para Sahaja Yoga'dan farklıdır.
And one should not talk like this. It brings bad a name to Sahaja Yoga.
Ve kimse böyle konuşmamalı. Bu, Sahaja Yoga'nın adını kötüye çıkarır.
Nobody should talk. Whatever is the problem of money you can find it out.
Kimse konuşmamalı. Para sorunu ne olursa olsun, bir çözüm bulabilirsiniz.
But why talk about it? It’s a wrong thing.
Ama neden bunun hakkında konuşasanız ki? Bu yanlış bir şey.
[To the baby] No? No, come. You come to Me for a while. All right?
[Bebeğe] Hayır mı? Hayır, gel. Bir süreliğine Bana gel. Tamam mı?
I didn’t take her so she…
Onu almadım, o yüzden…
[Laughter]
Bu oyuncak bebek,
This dolly baby, this dolly baby. She doesn’t cry.
bu oyuncak bebek. Ağlamıyor.
Dolly baby doesn’t cry.
Oyuncak bebek ağlamıyor.
Or you shout or not or scream sometimes, little bit.
Ya da bazen bağırırsın ya da çığlık atarsın, birazcık.
[Shri Mataji chuckles]
Gülümsemesine bak.
Look at the smile. Look at that, another one.
Şuna bak, bir tane daha.
Yes, still sleeping.
Evet, hala uyuyor.
No, no, I’m talking to you.
Hayır, hayır, seninle konuşuyorum.
No, no, I’m not talking to you, I’m not talking to anybody else.
Hayır, hayır, seninle konuşmuyorum, kimseyle konuşmuyorum. Sadece seninle konuşuyorum.
I’m just talking to you. All right?
Tamam mı? Ne oldu? Ne oldu? Ne oldu?
What happened? What happened? What happened? No, no, no, no.
Hayır, hayır, hayır, hayır. Onun alması gerekiyor.
Oh, no, no, no, no, no. She has to take. Dolly.
Dolly? Oh, ne oldu? Ne oldu?
Oh, what happened? What happened?
Diğer kişi ile konuşmaya başladım, onunla konuşmadım.
I just started talking to him and not to her. He?
Acıktı mı? Sanırım acıktı.
Is she hungry? I think she is. Oh, she is hungry. He?
Oh, acıktı.
What happened?
Ne oldu?
She is hungry, I think. She is hungry.
Sanırım acıktı. Acıktı.
Work very hard.
Çok çalış...
You have something too.
Senin de bir şeyin var.
All right, all right. She is hungry.
Tamam, tamam. O aç. Ona biberon ver.
Get her some
Biberon hazırladın mı, başladın mı? Yogini: Ben bir tane hazırladım.
book. You make a bottle, you have started?
Shri Mataji: Tamam, o zaman versen iyi olur.
Child: I ‘m gone one made up.
Şimdi ağlıyor.
So, what have you decided then?
Peki, neye karar verdin?
Sahaja Yogi: I have one idea which I believe-
Sahaja Yogi: Bir fikrim var, bence...
Shri Mataji: So just give Me.
Shri Mataji: Öyleyse Bana ver.
Sahaja Yogi: Paul had also had the idea that we should maybe make a, try to make a sort
Sahaja Yogi: Paul'un da bir fikri vardı, belki de Sahaja Yoga hakkında bir tür belgesel,
of a documentary, film documentary about Sahaja Yoga. Perhaps on video. And then, I don’t know,
film belgeseli yapmalıyız diye... Muhtemelen video olarak.
twenty minutes, half an hour or something. Then we could make copies of it, you see.
Ve sonra, bilmiyorum, yirmi dakika, yarım saat falan. Sonra da kopyalarını çıkarabiliriz.
Shri Mataji: Whenever, but first actors should be all right now.
Shri Mataji: Ne zaman olursa olsun ama önce oyuncuların hazır olması lazım.
Yes. You are so, thank you.
Evet. Çok teşekkür ederim.
Shri Mataji: I think [unclear] this is your tape and all that.
Shri Mataji: Sanırım [belirsiz]… Bu senin kasetin ve diğerleri…
I told Paul, I don’t know if you understood Me or not.
Paul'a söyledim, Beni anladın mı, anlamadın mı? Bilmiyorum.
It is only handled when there are people to see it.
Sadece izleyecek insanlar olduğunda kullanılıyor.
Where do we have?
Nerede var?
Sahaja Yogi: Well, what I thought, there was one thing we could perhaps
Sahaja Yogi: Şey, düşündüğüm şey, belki televizyonda
then approach people on television and show them, you see. Because-
insanlara yaklaşıp onlara gösterebiliriz. Çünkü…
Shri Mataji: But whom are you going to show?
Shri Mataji: Ama kime göstereceksin?
Sahaja Yogi: Well, I don’t know, but if you-
Sahaja Yogi: Şey, bilmiyorum ama eğer siz…
Shri Mataji: That’s the main point, you know. You do all the experiments, you see.
Shri Mataji: Asıl mesele bu, biliyorsunuz. Tüm deneyleri yapıyorsunuz, görüyorsunuz.
He came to me and he told me, make a video tape of things.
O, Bana geldi ve Bana, ''Olayların video kasetini çekin.'' dedi.
We have a reward, lots of things, but whom to show?
Ödülümüz var, birçok şeyimiz var ama kime göstereceğiz?
Only we have to see ourselves.
Sadece kendimizi görmemiz gerekiyor.
Another Sahaja Yogi: There is a program on Sundays, I think it is, on television,
Başka bir Sahaja Yogi: Sanırım Pazar günleri televizyonda,
which allows people to show, individuals and groups of people, they have their own program.
insanların, bireylerin ve grupların kendi programlarını göstermelerine izin veren bir program var.
Shri Mataji: We have been-
Shri Mataji: Biz…
Sahaja Yogi: And other things like that.
Sahaja Yogi: Ve bunun gibi başka şeyler.
Shri Mataji: We have been asking them to give us even five minutes.
Shri Mataji: Onlardan bize beş dakika bile versinler, diye rica ediyoruz.
They have not yet given us.
Henüz vermediler.
Sahaja Yogi: But the thing is, Mother, if we produce
Sahaja Yogi: Ama mesele şu ki, Anne, eğer
something which they could just see easily, then that would give them a much better idea
onların kolayca görebilecekleri bir şey üretirsek,
of the quality of the thing. And it wouldn’t actually be so expensive.
o zaman bunun kalitesini çok daha iyi anlayabilirler. Ve aslında çok pahalı da olmaz.
Shri Mataji: We have a film already with him.
Shri Mataji: Onunla zaten bir filmimiz var.
Now what you have to do is to edit it and do it properly, you see.
Şimdi yapmanız gereken şey, onu düzenlemek ve düzgün bir şekilde yapmak...
Sahaja Yogi: We can make one up quite cheaply, Mother. We can just,
Anlıyor musunuz? Sahaja Yogi: Oldukça ucuza bir tane yapabiliriz, Anne.
if we need to shoot the whole film, we can just hire the equipment for few days.
Eğer tüm filmi çekmemiz gerekirse, ekipmanı birkaç günlüğüne kiralayabiliriz.
Shri Mataji: No, that’s not difficult. What I’m saying that, we have already got to film.
Shri Mataji: Hayır, bu zor değil. Demek istediğim, filmimiz zaten hazır.
[To the Sahaja Yogini] Now can you go out and open the door?
[Sahaja Yogini'ye] Şimdi dışarı çıkıp kapıyı açabilir misin?
Now, the only thing you have to do is to get the photographs, I mean here to film it.
Şimdi yapman gereken tek şey fotoğrafları almak, yani burayı filme almak.
He has got already a thing to film.
O zaten filme alacak bir şey var.
Get it edited, you see. And when you come to India this time, people,
Düzenle, anladın mı? Ve bu sefer Hindistan'a geldiğinde insanlar,
then we can get more films from India, add them up together.
o zaman Hindistan'dan daha fazla film alabiliriz, hepsini bir araya getirebiliriz.
This time when I go, I think I can borrow your camera or something and we can work it out.
Bu sefer gittiğimde, sanırım senin kameranı falan ödünç alabilirim ve bunu halledebiliriz.
Sahaja Yogi: That’s what I was thinking, Mother.
Sahaja Yogi: Ben de öyle düşünüyordum, Anne.
Shri Mataji: And then, all that put together, then we can make a nice film here.
Shri Mataji: Ve sonra, hepsini bir araya getirip, burada güzel bir film yapabiliriz.
Sahaja Yogi: Yes, that’s what I thought that we can have.
Sahaja Yogi: Evet, ben de öyle yapabileceğimizi düşünmüştüm.
Shri Mataji: Well, work it out. That is one of mine.
Shri Mataji: Peki, halledin. Bu benim fikirlerimden biri.
Sahaja Yogi: And we could have some sort of introduction to
Sahaja Yogi: Ve Sahaja Yoga'nın ne olduğunu açıklayan
explaining what Sahaja Yoga is as well. Showing the chart, and so introduce.
bir tür giriş de yapabiliriz. Tabloyu gösterip tanıtabiliriz.
Shri Mataji: You can do it. But these are little confusing ones, you see.
Shri Mataji: Yapabilirsiniz. Ama bunlar biraz kafa karıştırıcı, görüyorsunuz.
Like puja and all that.
Puja ve benzeri şeyler gibi...
Sahaja Yogi: Oh no, it would have to be –
Sahaja Yogi: Hayır, öyle olmak zorunda değil…
Shri Mataji: But I’ll have to take a film.
Shri Mataji: Ama bir film çekmem gerekecek.
Hello, Don, hello, how are you? May God bless you.
Merhaba Don, merhaba, nasılsıın? Tanrı seni kutsasın.
I’ll take a film – come along, sit down -from here.
Bir film çekeceğim, gel, otur, buradan.
And Raman is very good at it. And I’ll ask him to help Me there.
Raman bu konuda çok iyidir. Ondan Bana yardım etmesini isteyeceğim.
He’s
Bana projektörünü verecek,
going to give Me his projector, which will you, I’ll bring it to London.
sen de onu Londra'ya getireceksin.
We can use that projector.
O projektörü kullanabiliriz.
But you see, the film is, the film that they have here is 60 millimetres, isn’t it?
Ama bak, film, burada olan film altmış milimetre, değil mi?
Sahaja Yogi: What we have is Super 8. They also have a Super 8 film there. That’s how I know.
Sahaja Yogi: Bizimki Super sekiz. Onların da Super sekiz filmi var. O yüzden biliyorum.
Shri Mataji: Just find out. Because somebody told Me that this cannot be converted into that.
Shri Mataji: Bir araştıralım. Çünkü biri Bana bunun ona dönüştürülemeyeceğini söyledi.
Sahaja Yogi: Into what?
Sahaja Yogi: Neye?
Shri Mataji: Into films on the TV.
Shri Mataji: Televizyondaki filmlere.
Shri Mataji: Why don’t you find out? You see, somebody, do you know in the…
Shri Mataji: Neden araştırmıyorsun? Biliyor musun, biri, biliyor musun…
Sahaja Yogi: Quite a lot, Mother. I’ve known, it’s used quite a lot because
Sahaja Yogi: Oldukça fazla, Anne. Bunun oldukça sık kullanıldığını biliyorum
TV cameramen take out their Super 8 sometimes when they can’t film in a situation. And then they film
çünkü televizyon kameramanları bazen bir durumda çekim yapamadıklarında Super sekizlerini çıkarırlar.
with Super 8, and then at the TV studios, they have a machine which converts it onto video tape.
Sonra Super sekiz ile çekim yaparlar ve televizyon stüdyolarında bunu video kasete dönüştüren bir makine var.
Shri Mataji: Ah, you can do it. No problem.
Shri Mataji: Ah, bunu yapabilirsiniz. Sorun yok.
Another Sahaja Yogi: We might be able to use it for programs,
Sahaja Yogi: Bunu programlar için kullanabiliriz Anne.
Mother. I mean, in remote places, if you’re not going Mother, we could.
Yani, uzak yerlerde eğer Siz gitmezseniz, biz gidebiliriz.
I mean, lots of people would come to see a film when they wouldn’t come to see her
Yani, birçok insan onu görmeye gelmezken, bir film izlemeye gelirler, anlarsın ya...
for a lecture, you know what I mean. Just because you produce some sort of a
Sadece bir şey ürettiğiniz için
thing, people would come and see it.
insanlar gelip izlerler.
Shri Mataji: We can do it. We can get it from India.
Shri Mataji: Yapabiliriz. Hindistan'dan getirebiliriz.
I mean, I had this idea before also.
Yani, bu fikir daha önce de aklıma gelmişti.
That’s one of the things we could do.
Yapabileceğimiz şeylerden biri bu.
But his idea was different. What idea Paul gave Me was of no use, I thought.
Ama onun fikri farklıydı. Paul'un Bana verdiği fikir işe yaramazdı, diye düşündüm.
He said that why not we all get a video and see the program.
Neden hepimiz bir video alıp programı izlemiyoruz, dedi.
I said, what’s the use? We are the seers and we are the doers.
Ben de bunun ne faydası var, dedim. Biz görenler ve yapanlarız.
Sahaja Yogi: No, no, I wasn’t thinking in that line.
Sahaja Yogi: Hayır, hayır, ben öyle düşünmüyordum.
Shri Mataji: So, that won’t be of use. But, of a very wide coverage.
Shri Mataji: Yani, bunun bir faydası olmaz. Ama çok geniş bir kitleye ulaşır.
Another Sahaja Yogi: And then, one could just show it,
Sahaja Yogi: Ve sonra, programa gelmeyenlere
if you’re not coming to the program, as an introduction into Sahaja Yoga.
Sahaja Yoga'ya giriş olarak gösterebiliriz .
Sahaja Yogi: We could show some shots of you giving us introductory speech at a
Sahaja Yogi: Belki de halka açık bir programda bize giriş konuşması yaparkenki
public program, perhaps. And we could show people experiencing Realization.
bazı görüntüleri gösterebiliriz. Ve aydınlanmayı deneyimleyen insanları gösterebiliriz.
Shri Mataji: Are baba, where I am also available,
Shri Mataji: Arey Baba, Benim de bulunduğum yerlerde,
there are hardly three people.
neredeyse üç kişi bile yok.
Where is such an audience? What I am saying that, I am quite available.
Böyle bir izleyici kitlesi nerede? Demek istediğim, Ben oldukça uygunum.
I mean, I have been available in Rome.
Yani, Roma'da da uygunum.
Of course, there were not one person.
Tabii ki, tek bir kişi bile yoktu.
We had to pay for the hall, we had to pay for the room,
Salonun parasını ödemek zorunda kaldık, odanın parasını ödemek zorunda kaldık
and they did not even publish.
ve onlar yayınlamadılar bile.
Now, Gregoire is going to do the next time.
Şimdi, Gregoire bir dahaki sefere yapacak.
So this is what it is, you see.
Durum bu, anlıyor musun?
Sahaja Yogi: But I think it might make a difference for getting publicity on television.
Sahaja Yogi: Ama bence televizyonda reklam yapmak bir fark yaratabilir.
If we can show them something, you see, which they can see easily.
Onlara kolayca görebilecekleri bir şey gösterebilirsek.
Shri Mataji: That is one thing. That is different, altogether.
Shri Mataji: Bu başka bir şey. Bu tamamen farklı.
Another Sahaja Yogi: If you have more chance than just writing them a letter, you see.
Sahaja Yogi: Onlara mektup yazmaktan daha fazla şansınız varsa, anlıyor musunuz?
Shri Mataji: No, no, that is much better.
Shri Mataji: Hayır, hayır, bu çok daha iyi.
There I agree with you that we should give him a complete thing done,
O konuda size katılıyorum, ona tam bir şey sunmalıyız,
plus substantiated by the doctors and things that they have seen it, you see.
ayrıca doktorlar tarafından doğrulanmış ve onların gördükleri şeyler, anlıyor musunuz?
Sahaja Yogi: Not now, we discussed with Paul this film idea a long time ago, because we have
Sahaja Yog: Şimdi değil, bu film fikrini uzun zaman önce Paul ile tartıştık
got a lot of material, you see. And he only thinks that he may get, he may wish to buy a video tape.
çünkü çok fazla materyalimiz var, anlıyor musunuz? Ve o sadece alabileceğini, bir video kaset satın almak isteyebileceğini düşünüyor.
Shri Mataji: Oh, no, that is, that is something I just don’t understand.
Shri Mataji: Oh, hayır, bu, Bu benim anlayamadığım bir şey.
Sahaja Yogi: But I say, we have got this super 8, we can do a lot professional type films,
Sahaja Yogi: Ama diyorum ki, bu super sekizimiz var,
as long as we get somebody, you see, because I used to make films sometimes, you see.
birini bulduğumuz sürece çok profesyonel filmler yapabiliriz çünkü ben bazen film yapardım.
Shri Mataji: No, no. But what I am trying to tell you, video, this thing is not necessary.
Shri Mataji: Hayır, hayır. Ama size söylemeye çalıştığım şey, video, bu şey gerekli değil.
What you have to do is to prepare a film on Sahaja Yoga.
Yapmanız gereken şey, Sahaja Yoga hakkında bir film hazırlamak.
Sahaja Yogi: Yes.
Sahaja Yogi: Evet.
Shri Mataji: You have to still get more material, which I will get now.
Shri Mataji: Hala daha fazla malzeme almanız gerekiyor, Ben şimdi alacağım.
If I am going with this idea, I will get it up to Australia, all these things. All right?
Bu fikri uygulayacaksam, Avustralya'ya kadar getireceğim, tüm bunları. Tamam mı?
Once you have these things with you, then you assemble them and make a proper commentary
Bunları aldığınızda, onları bir araya getirip uygun bir yorum yazın
and make a Sahaja Yoga film.
ve bir Sahaja Yoga filmi yapın.
That you can do it here, later on.
Bunu burada, daha sonra yapabilirsiniz.
That’s a different thing, but this video business, I don’t fit it to my head.
Bu farklı bir şey ama bu video işi, kafam almıyor.
There is no need just now for having a video.
Şu anda videoya gerek yok.
You see, that is diverting the attention. All right?
Bu dikkatleri dağıtıyor. Tamam mı?
Sahaja Yogi: But there is, I asked other to do something about making a
Sahaja Yogi: Ama var, ben başkasına
film on Sahaja Yoga, as such. I mean the chakras.
Sahaja Yoga hakkında bir film yapması için bir şey istedim. Yani çakralar hakkında...
But what we need is a good subject with a good catch, where it’s pulsating. To film, you see.
Ama bizim ihtiyacımız olan şey, iyi bir konu ve iyi bir çekicilik, heyecan verici bir şey. Film çekmek için, anlarsınız ya.
Shri Mataji: We have got that.
Shri Mataji: Bizde var.
Sahaja Yogi: No, we haven’t got that, unfortunately.
Sahaja Yogi: Hayır, maalesef bizde yok.
Shri Mataji: Where is it? In India?
Shri Mataji: Nerede? Hindistan'da mı?
Sahaja Yogi: No, we haven’t got one. We need a subject with a very good catch.
Sahaja Yogi: Hayır, bizde yok. Çok iyi bir konusu olan bir konuya ihtiyacımız var.
Shri Mataji: No, no, we have filmed it, India has got it.
Shri Mataji: Hayır, hayır, biz filme aldık, Hindistan'da var.
Sahaja Yogi: Yes, maybe it is in India. It’s not a big deal which we sent last year, is it?
Sahaja Yogi: Evet, belki Hindistan'dadır. Geçen yıl gönderdiğimiz şey önemli değil, değil mi?
Shri Mataji: In India they have got this. I have seen it.
Shri Mataji: Hindistan'da var. Gördüm.
Sahaja Yogi: Because I knew we had one once,
Sahaja Yogi: Çünkü bir zamanlar bir tane olduğunu biliyordum.
but later we need this. It’s no longer here with me, you see.
Ama sonra buna ihtiyacımız oldu.
Shri Mataji:
Artık bende yok, görüyorsunuz.
There is one with all these things.
Shri Mataji: Bütün bunları içeren bir tane var.
So we will have to assemble and find out.
O yüzden bir araya gelip bulmamız gerekecek.
Sahaja Yogi: To edit and put a commentary and some, you know.
Sahaja Yogi: Düzenlemek ve yorum eklemek için, bilirsiniz.
Shri Mataji: I’ll get you that. That I’ll get you.
Shri Mataji: Size onu getireceğim. Sana onu getireceğim.
All these things, you
Bütün bu şeyler, görüyorsun...
see, practical things. We can do that.
Pratik şeyler... Bunu yapabiliriz.
Now, what else? This is one suggestion.
Şimdi, başka ne var? Bu bir öneri.
But this is only for publicity to the BBC people, if they want to see it.
Ama bu sadece BBC çalışanlarına tanıtım için, eğer görmek isterlerse...
But we can make it. What else is the suggestion?
Ama bunu yapabiliriz. Başka öneri var mı?
Sahaja Yogi: Mother, there are hundreds of groups, in England.
Sahaja Yogi: Anne, İngiltere'de yüzlerce grup var.
Shri Mataji: He?
Shri Mataji: Hıh…
Sahaja Yogi: There are hundreds of different groups and societies and everything.
Sahaja Yogi: Yüzlerce farklı grup, dernek ve her şey var.
We can go and give talks to them.
Gidip onlarla konuşabiliriz.
Sahaja Yogi: Direct.
Shri Mataji: Doğrudan.
Shri Mataji:
Sahaja Yogi: Doğrudan.
For that, I was thinking a pamphlet must be made ready
Shri Mataji: Bunun için, bir broşür hazırlanmalı
and should be sent to these groups.
ve bu gruplara gönderilmeli diye düşünüyorum.
And see if they are willing to accept it.
Ve kabul etmeye istekli olup olmadıklarını görmeliyiz.
We can make a nice pamphlet for them.
Onlar için güzel bir broşür hazırlayabiliriz.
What is the third? Write it down all these points, sir:
Üçüncüsü nedir? Tüm bu noktaları yazın.
making a film, then making a pamphlet for the groups.
Bir film yapmak, sonra gruplar için bir broşür hazırlamak...
Now get the addresses of all these groups.
Şimdi tüm bu grupların adreslerini alın.
Sahaja Yogi: The pre-introduction, I think, is a very good idea.
Sahaja Yogi: Ön tanıtım, bence çok iyi bir fikir.
Shri Mataji: It’s very simple directly.
Shri Mataji: Çok basit ve doğrudan.
Sahaja Yogi: Because a lot of people come with the
Sahaja Yogi: Çünkü birçok insan,
idea that Self-realization – and they’ve heard from other
aydınlanma ile ilgili bir fikirle geliyor ve diğer öğretmenlerden
teachers and gurus [unclear] – Self-realization is hard committed and some sudden foolish show.
ve gurulardan aydınlanmanın zor bir taahhüt ve ani bir aptalca gösteri olduğunu duymuşlar.
Shri Mataji: Actualization, what do you expect? It’s the point.
Shri Mataji: Aydınlanma, ne bekliyorsunuz? Asıl mesele bu. Hıh?
Sahaja Yogi: The people just think that their whole life is going to change and the world is
Sahaja Yogi: İnsanlar, aydınlanmaya ulaştıklarında
going to look different instantaneously when they’ve got Self-realization.
tüm hayatlarının değişeceğini ve dünyanın aniden farklı görüneceğini düşünüyorlar.
Shri Mataji: It does with many. But I mean it takes time for some.
Shri Mataji: Birçoğu için öyle oluyor. Ama bazıları için zaman alıyor, demek istiyorum.
Sahaja Yogi: I heard someone mention that
Sahaja Yogi: Birinin şöyle bir şey söylediğini duydum:
it may be good to have some type of – when we’ve got a person, and we’ve given self-realization,
Bir kişiye aydınlanma verdiğimizde aslında onlara aydınlanma aldıklarını
that we don’t actually tell them that they’ve got their Self-realization yet,
söylemememiz iyi olabilir; üzerinde çalışarak
that they’ve got to work it out for it.
fark etmeleri gerektiğini söyleyelim.
Shri Mataji: No, no, no, no. Whatever it is, we have to tell them.
Shri Mataji: Hayır, hayır, hayır, hayır. Ne olursa olsun, onlara söylemeliyiz.
No use hiding it. It is Self-realization, no doubt.
Saklamanın bir anlamı yok. Bu aydınlanma, şüphesiz…
But the problem with all these people in the West is, that they don’t know what is Self-realization.
Ama Batı'daki tüm bu insanların sorunu, aydınlanmanın ne olduğunu bilmemeleri.
So, they are to be awakened.
Bu yüzden, uyanmaları gerekiyor.
Because they are naïve, they don’t know what to expect.
Naif oldukları için, ne bekleyeceklerini bilmiyorlar.
What is Self-realization, and Indian knows better, much better.
Aydınlanma nedir? Ve Hintliler bunu çok daha iyi bilirler.
Sahaja Yogi: They are all looking for it but they don’t know what it is.
Sahaja Yogi: Hepsi bunu arıyor ama ne olduğunu bilmiyorlar.
Shri Mataji: That’s the introduction. Now you get the list of all the other motels.
Shri Mataji: Bu bir giriş. Şimdi diğer tüm motellerin listesini al.
Sahaja Yogi: This week, we had our first meeting at university again. And the experience goes like
Sahaja Yogi: Bu hafta, üniversitede yine ilk toplantımızı yaptık. Ve deneyimlerimiz şu şekilde oldu:
this. When you talk about yoga, or when people read about yoga, it is Hatha Yoga
Yoga hakkında konuştuğunuzda veya insanlar yoga hakkında okuduklarında,
for those people. One only stayed eventually, you see, and we started to work with her, because she
bu insanlar için Hatha Yoga'dır. Sonunda sadece biri kaldı ve onunla çalışmaya başladık çünkü
was starting to sweat from ‘guru Raj’, you see. She may come again. But I think we do have to
"Guru Raj"dan rahatsız olmaya başlamış. Belki tekrar gelir. Ama bence
get in the pamphlet or different pamphlets for different types of gurus. As the people who speak
farklı türdeki gurular için broşür veya farklı broşürler hazırlamalıyız.
must really know those gurus, what are their favours, etc.
Konuşan insanlar  bu guruları gerçekten tanımalı, onların tercihlerini bilmeli vb.
Shri Mataji: You know, the thing is, if you write it down is a dangerous thing. Because –
Shri Mataji: Biliyorsunuz, mesele şu ki, bunu yazmak tehlikeli bir şey. Çünkü...
Sahaja Yogi: For ourselves.
Sahaja Yogi: Kendimiz için.
[Laughter]
Shri Mataji: Kendimiz için sorun yok.
But if you write it down, this thing, you will develop a problem.
Ama bunu yazarsanız, bir sorun çıkar.
I say because they can try to trouble us and I don’t want to have any controversy.
Çünkü bize sorun çıkarmaya çalışabilirler ve Ben herhangi bir tartışma istemiyorum.
So what you can do in the group when you have the meetings,
Öyleyse grupta yapabileceğiniz şey:
then if somebody says that, “I am such and such, disciple of such and such, and
Toplantılarda, biri şöyle derse, "Ben falanca falanca'nın öğrencisiyim ve
I have been working on this”.
bunun üzerinde çalışıyorum",
You should say, “All right, we tell you about it, how to work it out “.
"Tamam, sana nasıl çözebileceğini anlatacağız" demelisiniz.
But keep it a separate session with that person, individually.
Ama bunu o kişiyle ayrı bir oturumda, birebir yapın.
But not in the public meetings.
Halka açık toplantılarda değil.
Because I have seen, even I cannot handle sometimes the way people are
Çünkü gördüm ki, bazen insanların bu gurulara bağımlılıklarını
addicted to these gurus.
Ben bile idare edemiyorum.
So, if you just start any controversy,
Yani, herhangi bir tartışma başlatırsanız
they will have a greater chance of troubling us, so keep them out.
bizi rahatsız etme şansları daha fazla olur, bu yüzden onları dışarıda tutun.
You see, our attitude should be those who want to come can come,
Görüyorsunuz, bizim tutumumuz şöyle olmalı: Gelmek isteyenler gelebilir,
those who do not want to come, cannot come.
gelmek istemeyenler gelemez.
But we want to give them a clear-cut picture of what positively, what things are.
Ama onlara olumlu olan şeylerin, neyin ne olduğunu net bir şekilde anlatmak istiyoruz.
The negativity we need not mention just now.
Şu anda negativitelerden bahsetmemize gerek yok.
Because if you mention the negativity,
Çünkü negativitelerden bahsederseniz,
there could be legal problem, any type of a problem can come up.
yasal sorunlar, her türlü sorun ortaya çıkabilir.
So just now we don’t want any confrontation.
Şu anda herhangi bir çatışma istemiyoruz.
We’ll just give, “This is the picture,
Sadece şunu söyleyeceğiz: "Durum bu,
this is what you have to achieve, this is what you have to get”.
başarmanız gereken budur, elde etmeniz gereken budur."
Now somebody comes with the idea that, “I am into such and such “, so what about it?
Şimdi biri gelip "Ben şununla ilgileniyorum" derse, ne yapacaksınız?
You say, “Did you find it?” “No”. “So… “.
"Buldunuz mu?" diye sorarsınız.
You can put this there, that you have not yet found it, all right?
“Hayır.” “Öyleyse…” Bunu oraya koyabilirsin, henüz bulamadın, tamam mı?
This is how you can talk.
Böyle konuşabilirsin.
But not in the, I mean, individual cases we should not discuss,
Ama bireysel vakalarda tartışmamalıyız,
neither in general also we should talk much about it.
genel olarak da fazla konuşmamalıyız.
Because unnecessarily, you see, to begin with, it creates a- you know,
Çünkü gereksiz yere, görüyorsun, başlangıçta, bu bir, biliyorsun,
it’s so naive, the whole attitude of the West is,
çok naif, Batı'nın tüm tutumu,
that they think, you see, if God is there, then how can there be evil?
onların düşündüğü gibi, Tanrı varsa nasıl kötülük olabilir?
First of all, is it all the responsibility of God.
Öncelikle, her şeyin sorumluluğu Tanrı'ya mı ait?
And the responsibility of man is to be evil and the responsibility of
İnsanın sorumluluğu kötülük yapmak,
God is not to keep evil, you see.
Tanrı'nın sorumluluğu ise kötülüğü engellemek, anlıyor musun?
This is what is the idea of the West is.
Batı'nın düşüncesi budur.
[Shri Mataji chuckles]
İkincisi, eğer Tanrı sevgiyse,
Secondly, if God is love, then how can you say something is bad?
o zaman bir şeyin kötü olduğunu nasıl söyleyebilirsiniz?
You see, this is second nonsensical idea they have.
Bu, onların ikinci saçma fikri.
This is the worst idea that one can have, is to say God is love.
Tanrı'nın sevgi olduğunu söylemek, bir insanın sahip olabileceği en kötü fikir.
But in his love, He kills people. He is a wrathful God. It’s written.
Ama O, sevgisiyle insanları öldürür. O öfkeli bir Tanrı'dır. Bu yazılıdır.
It’s clearly written, He is a wrathful God and He can bring wrath on you.
Bu açıkça yazılmıştır. O, öfkeli bir Tanrı'dır ve size gazap getirebilir.
If He loves everyone, then why does He bring wrath, you see?
Eğer herkesi seviyorsa, neden gazap getiriyor, anlıyor musunuz?
This is second idea, which is very funny and which is really very confusing for people to understand,
Bu ikinci fikir, çok komik ve insanların anlaması için gerçekten çok kafa karıştırıcı
that there are people who are absolutely evil.
çünkü kesinlikle kötü insanlar var.
There’s no God in them.
Onların içinde Tanrı yok.
So, this is the second idea which with which they come forward.
Bu, onların ortaya attığı ikinci fikir.
Then they say that, “We respect every person who talks of God”.
Sonra diyorlar ki, “Tanrı'dan bahseden herkese saygı duyuyoruz”.
Now what do you say to that?
Peki buna ne cevap vereceksiniz?
Sahaja Yogini: Mother, I think the most convincing thing, for people,
Sahaja Yogini: Anne, bence insanlar için en ikna edici şey,
is when they actually start seeing and experiencing the damage that these people
bu insanların yaptıkları zararı gerçekten görmeye ve deneyimlemeye başladıkları zaman.
have done. Because otherwise, it’s still only a discussion.
Çünkü aksi takdirde, bu sadece bir tartışma olur.
Shri Mataji: Discussion level you cannot talk.
Shri Mataji: Tartışma düzeyinde konuşamazsınız.
Discussion level they will win over.
Tartışma düzeyinde onlar kazanır.
You see, and then the last of all is this, that when you start discussing with them,
Sonra da en sonuncusu şudur. Onlarla tartışmaya başladığınızda,
then you just get fed up.
sonunda bıkarsınız.
And you say, “Oh no, let it be, doesn’t matter”.
Ve "Oh hayır, boş ver, önemli değil." dersiniz.
Then they’ll say, “Look at this, they are supposed to be Yogis and they have no patience”.
O zaman onlar da "Bakın, bunlar Yogi olması gereken insanlar ve hiç sabırları yok" derler.
Even if they beat you, you are supposed to say, “All right”.
Sizi dövseler bile, "Tamam" demelisiniz.
One person said, “What about God? Christ said that
Birisi der ki, "Peki ya Tanrı?
if somebody slaps on you or one cheek, then turn the other”.
İsa, biri size bir tokat atarsa, diğer yanağınızı da çevirin."
I said, “That is the only solution with mad people, that’s why. Otherwise it – “
Ben de diyorum ki, bu deli insanlara karşı tek çözümdür, bu yüzden.
[Laughter]
Aksi takdirde…
That’s the only way they’ll get shocked when you tell them that, “Beat me on the other cheek”.
Onlara "Diğer yanağımı da vur" dediğinizde şok olacakları tek yol budur.
Nobody will beat you, but that’s how you can stop them.
Kimse sizi dövmez ama onları bu şekilde durdurabilirsiniz.
That’s what He was meaning.
O da bunu kastetmişti.
So, that was the only solution for mad people, that’s why He said it.
Yani, bu deli insanlar için tek çözümdü. Çılgın insanlar için tek çözüm buydu.
But this is the idea: if you are a saint, then you must suffer.
Bu yüzden öyle söyledi. Ama fikir şu: Eğer bir azizsen, o zaman acı çekmelisin.
They have a right to boss over you.
Onların sana patronluk taslama hakkı var.
Because of these kinds of ideas, you have to be very, very careful with them, no doubt.
Bu tür fikirler yüzünden, onlara karşı çok, çok dikkatli olmalısın. Şüphesiz...
So, all these things are there.
Yani, tüm bunlar var.
And last lecture in Bonn, you see, when Thomas was very,
Ve Bonn'daki son konuşmamda
very upset about people, how they are going to aggress.
Thomas, insanların saldırganlıklarından dolayı çok çok üzgündü.
And some were saying, “These are Eastern ideas and these are Western ideas, and this and that”.
Bazıları "Bunlar Doğu fikirleri" ve "Bunlar Batı fikirleri" şu bu, diyordu.
Then I lashed them, I wish you could get my tape from him.
Sonra onları azarladım, keşke ondan kasetimi alabilseydiniz.
And then I told the arrogance of the West.
Sonra Batı'nın kibirinden bahsettim.
I said, it’s quite summed up very well, the way they are arrogant about things
Dedim ki, "Bu çok iyi özetlenmiş, bazı konularda kibirli davranıyorlar
and they think no end of themselves.
ve kendilerini çok beğeniyorlar."
And this idea of the West and the East doesn’t exist in my head.
Batı ve Doğu fikri Benim kafamda yok.
I said, “The West has done the outgrowing of a tree. What about the roots?
"Batı, bir ağacın büyümesini sağladı" dedim. Peki ya kökleri?
Who has to look after the roots?
Köklere kim bakacak?
The poor East people, Eastern people are looking after the roots
Zavallı Doğu halkı, Doğu halkı köklere bakıyor
and you are just outdoing your tree, what about your resources?
ve siz sadece ağacınızı büyütüyorsunuz, kaynaklarınız ne olacak?
You should find it out, otherwise you’d go mad”.
Bunu bulmalısınız, yoksa delireceksiniz."
And I mean, they are, no doubt about it.
Ve Bence, hiç şüphesiz öyle.
But the worst part I heard was, that now Switzerland is highest in society, more than
Ama duyduğum en kötü şey; şu anda İsviçre'nin,
Sweden.
İsveç'ten daha yüksek bir toplum olduğuydu.
And the second thing I heard about was,
İkinci duyduğum şey ise,
that out of five families in Switzerland only one can produce children, can.
İsviçre'deki beş aileden sadece birinin çocuk sahibi olabildiğiydi.
This is the situation. They cannot produce children.
Durum bu. Çocuk sahibi olamıyorlar.
And, there was a lady, she said, “I am very busy with Afghanistan”.
Ve bir bayan vardı, "Afganistan ile çok meşgulüm." dedi.
I said, “Afghanistan?”
Ben dedim ki, "Afganistan mı?"
She said, “I am collecting money for Afghanistan, I am doing this for Afghanistan”.
O dedi ki, "Afganistan için para topluyorum, bunu Afganistan için yapıyorum."
I said, “Now what, why is she concerned?”
"Peki şimdi, neden endişeleniyor?" dedim.
In her own family there are six and seven people who have committed suicide.
Kendi ailesinde intihar eden altı ya da yedi kişi var.
She worried about Afghanistan?
Afganistan için mi endişeleniyor?
This is another ego style, is to shift your attention from your own problems to others,
Bu da başka bir ego tarzı, dikkatini kendi sorunlarından başkalarına kaydırmak,
is to think of Afghanistan.
Afganistan'ı düşünmek.
I said, “Leave it alone now, why do you bother with it?”
"Bırak artık, neden bununla uğraşıyorsun?" dedim.
[Shri Mataji chuckles]
[Shri Mataji gülüyor]
She will still look after.
O yine de ilgilenecek,
“The more people who are going to commit suicide in your family”.
ailenizde intihar edenlerin sayısı ne kadar fazla olursa olsun…
Sahaja Yogi: It’s funny that all the big rakshasas have managed to find themselves in Switzerland.
Sahaja Yogi: Tüm büyük rakshasaların İsviçre'de kendilerini bulmuş olmaları komik.
Shri Mataji: Find?
Shri Mataji: Bulmak mı?
Sahaja Yogi: Find themselves in Switzerland,
Sahaja Yogi: Kendilerini İsviçre'de bulmuşlar,
have their headquarters there like Narakasura and all that.
orada karargahları var… Narakasura ve diğerleri gibi.
Shri Mataji:
Shri Mataji: Hepsi oradalar
All of them are there, you see, because it’s the most beautiful country in the whole world.
çünkü dünyanın en güzel ülkesi.
I would say we have some places like that in India, which I have in my view,
Hindistan'da da Benim görüşüme göre öyle yerler var,
but which are absolutely remote.
ama bunlar çok uzak.
But Switzerland is the most beautiful place, I mean such, such soothing scenes I have seen,
Ama İsviçre en güzel yer. Yani gördüğüm o kadar huzur verici manzaralar,
such beautiful, that you cannot get that kind of a thing anywhere else.
o kadar güzel ki... Başka hiçbir yerde böyle bir şey bulamazsınız.
So, that’s why. They want to use all the beauties with the money. Everything.
İşte bu yüzden. Onlar tüm güzellikleri parayla kullanmak istiyorlar. Her şeyi...
And Switzerland is one place they are very safe there, they think.
Ve İsviçre, onların çok güvende olduklarını düşündükleri bir yer.
Because Swiss government is only interested in money.
Çünkü İsviçre hükümeti sadece parayla ilgileniyor.
As long as they give money, it’s all right.
Para verdikleri sürece sorun yok.
So they have money and they give money, it’s a mutual understanding.
Yani onlar paraya sahipler ve para veriyorlar, bu karşılıklı bir anlaşma.
But what about the Queen of England going to see the Pope?
Peki ya İngiltere Kraliçesi'nin Papa'yı ziyareti?
I didn’t like it much.
Bunu pek sevmedim.
This is that fornication with the kings, is it the same?
Bu, krallarla zina yapmakla aynı şey mi?
But she’s a very sensible woman, I don’t know why she did it. She’s quite a – Humm?
Ama o çok mantıklı bir kadın, neden bunu yaptı bilmiyorum. O oldukça… Hmm?
Sahaja Yogi: [Unclear]. I mean in [unclear] lot of people ever heard
Sahaja Yogi: [Anlaşılmıyor]. Demek istediğim... [anlaşılmıyor] Birçok insan hiç duymadı mı?
Shri Mataji: Is it? Because of Brazil, is it?
Shri Mataji: Öyle mi? Brezilya yüzünden mi?
Sahaja Yogi: [Unclear]. Because of her son who wants to marry a Catholic.
Sahaja Yogi: [Anlaşılmıyor]. Katolik biriyle evlenmek isteyen oğlu yüzünden.
Shri Mataji: Huh? Son?
Shri Mataji: Ha? Oğlu mu…
Sahaja Yogi: Charles wants to marry a Catholic princess.
Sahaja Yogi: Charles, Katolik bir prensesle evlenmek istiyor.
Shri Mataji: That’s why.
Shri Mataji: Demek bu yüzden.
I don’t know why, when I just can’t understand.
Nedenini bilmiyorum, anlayamıyorum.
Maybe Brazil, when Brazil is full of bhoots, it’s absolutely negative.
Belki Brezilya, Brezilya bhootlarla dolu olduğundan, kesinlikle negatif.
And there is this Mexico, all full of bhoots. Nigeria, everywhere.
Ve Meksika da bhootlarla dolu. Nijerya, her yer…
Catholicism must have taken bhoots.
Katoliklik bhootları almış olmalı.
Not only, but Catholicism in Rome has really opened my eyes, you know.
Sadece bu değil, Roma'daki Katoliklik gerçekten gözlerimi açtı, biliyor musunuz.
The Catholics from Rome who talk to Me – you can call them Italians – shocking!
Benimle konuşan Roma'lı Katolikler, onlara İtalyanlar diyebilirsiniz, şok edici!
Shocking it is.
Gerçekten şok edici.
They said they are earning fifty thousand dollars per day.
Günde elli bin dolar kazandıklarını söylediler.
There are six hundred schools in Rome itself, run by the Vatican,
Roma'da Vatikan tarafından yönetilen altı yüz okul var ve
where there are six thousand children in every school.
her okulda altı bin çocuk var.
And the fee is so exorbitant, and poor people cannot pay for it.
Ücretler çok yüksek ve fakir insanlar bunu ödeyemiyor.
They are getting money from places like Chile, Argentina,
Şili, Arjantin gibi çok fakir
all developing countries who are very poor.
gelişmekte olan ülkelerden para alıyorlar.
And telling them, “You cannot have birth control”.
Ve onlara "Doğum kontrolü yapamazsınız" diyorlar.
And the priests cannot marry. Just imagine!
Ve rahipler evlenemezler. Düşünün bir!
Sahaja Yogi: The gold that is in Vatican.
Sahaja Yogi: Vatikan'daki altın.
Shri Mataji: The gold and that is a part from that, I have seen part of it myself.
Shri Mataji: Altın...
That can beat even source [unsure] property.
Bunun bir kısmı, Ben kendim bir kısmını gördüm.
Sahaja Yogi: It’s built Mother.
Bu, kaynak mülkiyeti bile geçebilir.
Shri Mataji: Hum?
[belirsiz] mülkü bile geçebilir.
Sahaja Yogi: It’s built on the site of the Emperor Nero’s old
Sahaja Yogi: Orası inşa edildi Anne.  İmparator Nero'nun eski
circus, you know, the Vatican.
sirkinin bulunduğu yere inşa edildi, bilirsiniz, Vatikan.
Shri Mataji: Built on the site of?
Shri Mataji: Nereye inşa edildi?
Sahaja Yogi: The Emperor Nero, you know, that big rock in there. Very near.
Sahaja Yogi: İmparator Nero, bilirsiniz, oradaki büyük kaya. Çok yakın.
Shri Mataji: Very near, yes. Nero’s house is there.
Shri Mataji: Çok yakın, evet. Nero'nun evi orada.
But, I must say this Michael Angelo slap them out.
Ama şunu söylemeliyim ki Michelangelo onları tokatladı.
[Baby is screaming] I have got it. He doesn’t like to stay seating. All right.
(Bebek ağlıyor) Oturmayı sevmiyor.
Sahaja Yogini: He doesn’t like people talking about things like this.
Sahaja Yogini: İnsanların böyle şeyler hakkında konuşmasını sevmiyor.
Whenever we talk about something negative, he starts so.
Ne zaman olumsuz bir şey hakkında konuşsak böyle yapmaya başlıyor.
Shri Mataji: Really? Oh! All right, all right, all right.
Shri Mataji: Gerçekten mi? Oh! Tamam, tamam, tamam...
Now this money, they were saying, these people,
Şimdi bu para, onlar diyorlardı ki… Bu insanlar,
that if he was Iran of Shah, we would have put him down.
eğer o İran Şah'ı olsaydı, onu devirirdik.
And they are very, very poor, you know. These people are very poor.
Ve onlar çok, çok fakirler, biliyorsunuz. Bu insanlar çok fakirler.
And they said, “All this money goes there. And God knows what they are doing. We cannot ask them.
Ve dediler ki, "Bütün bu para oraya gidiyor. Ve Tanrı bilir ne yapıyorlar. Onlara soramayız.
This is our own money. All the countries, those who are supporting them are very poor”.
Bu bizim paramız. Onları destekleyen tüm ülkeler çok fakir.
And they said, “Only one small little spark can
Ve dediler ki, "Sadece küçük bir kıvılcım
completely put them onto fire. That is the condition.
onları tamamen ateşe verebilir. Durum bu.
People are so angry with them”.
İnsanlar onlara çok kızgın."
And they said, “This one is just a showman fellow.
Ve dediler ki, "Bu adam sadece bir şovmen.
This pope is a politician”.
Bu papa, bir politikacı.
And also what you call that, pop singer.
Ve ayrıca, ne diyorsunuz, pop şarkıcısı.
“He is like a pop singer. He is a pop star. He is a pop star as well as a politician”.
O, bir pop şarkıcısı gibi. O, bir pop yıldızı. O, bir pop yıldızı olduğu kadar bir politikacı da."
He said, “And all the money of all the poor people, he is sucking and they live like Lords”.
Dedi ki, "Ve tüm fakir insanların tüm paralarını emiyor ve onlar lordlar gibi yaşıyorlar."
Really, I saw the house and I was amazed!
Gerçekten, evi gördüm ve hayretler içinde kaldım!
But Michel Angelo, he has put them right.
Ama Michelangelo, onları düzeltti.
His Christ and all that. That is Lambodhara, he has shown as Christ.
Onun İsa'sı ve tüm o şeyler. Bu Lambodhara, onu İsa olarak gösterdi.
I must show you. I got his paintings and these things. I will show you.
Size göstermeliyim. Onun resimlerini ve bu şeyleri aldım. Size göstereceğim.
The best part he has shown about Judas.
En iyi kısmı, Yahuda'yı gösterdiği kısım.
They are having the Last Supper thing.
Son Akşam Yemeği sahnesi var.
And Judas is sitting there, you see.
Yahuda orada oturuyor, görüyorsunuz.
Everybody has got a golden colour aura.
Herkesin altın rengi bir aurası var.
And this one has an opaque colour on him.
Ama bu adamın rengi opak.
And a bhoot is sitting here
Ve bir bhoot, sol Agnya'da oturmuş
at the Left Agnya, telling him something.
ona bir şey söylüyor.
[Shri Mataji is laughing]
En iyi kısmı bu.
He shows really a little bhoot sitting there.
Orada oturan küçük bir bhoot'u gösteriyor.
You see, they see so clearly the bhoot, you know.
Gördün mü, bhoot'u çok net görüyorlar.
And the Last Judgement that they have done on the main
Ve Son Yargı sahnesi var,
set of the roof, you see, the Sistine Chapel, they call it.
çatının ana bölümünde yaptıkları, bilirsiniz, Sistine Şapeli dedikleri yerde.
There, the Last Judgement is so beautiful and there Christ is shown as he was.
Orada Son Yargı çok güzel ve İsa Mesih’i olduğu gibi gösteriliyor.
But they could not just, that Jonah, they call him the Jonah on top.
Ama onlar, Jonah'ı, ona Jonah diyorlar, tepeye koyamadılar.
Jonah is nothing less but our Kalaki there, sitting on top, you see.
Jonah, bizim Kalki'den başka bir şey değil. Orada, tepeye oturmuş.
With a great force he is turning people down.
Büyük bir güçle insanları aşağıya çeviriyor.
Many people are taking birth and it’s beautiful this Last Judgement
Birçok insan doğumlarını alıyor ve bu Son Yargı çok güzel.
And Christ, at the Agnya, is very powerful.
Ve Agnya'daki İsa çok güçlü.
He is a Lambodhara with a big stomach and all that, very healthy standing there.
O, büyük bir göbeği olan bir Lambodhara ve çok sağlıklı bir şekilde orada duruyor.
And the Mother sitting at the back.
Ve Anne arkada oturuyor.
I must say Michel Angelo has put him right.
Michelangelo'nun O'nu doğru bir şekilde resmettiğini söylemeliyim.
He has also shown so many priests and priests going to Hell!
Ayrıca birçok rahibi ve rahiplerin cehenneme gittiğini de göstermiş!
[Laughter]
[Kahkaha]
I mean this is,
Demek istediğim,
and the Protestants are also horrible people, I think.
Protestanlar da korkunç insanlar, Bence.
I don’t know what to do with them.
Onlarla ne yapacağımı bilmiyorum.
They are in another way, horribly fanatics, you see, horribly fanatics.
Onlar başka bir şekilde, korkunç fanatikler, görüyorsunuz, korkunç fanatikler.
There was one priest who came, he was a Catholic priest, he came to see Me in ordinary dress.
Gelen bir rahip vardı, Katolik bir rahipti, sıradan kıyafetlerle Beni görmeye geldi.
And I must tell you some good news also.
Ve size bazı iyi haberler de vermeliyim.
So, I didn’t recognize him but he could not get Realisation.
Onu tanımadım ama o aydınlanma alamadı.
So, he wrote Me a letter through his friend that, “Mother, I must
Bana arkadaşı aracılığıyla bir mektup yazdı:
tell you I was seeking but in Catholicism, seeking is not allowed. And I am a priest
"Anne, Size söylemeliyim ki ben Katoliklikte arayış içindeydim ama Katoliklikte arayışa izin verilmiyor.
and I did not get married for the Savouries. So, I went to, I have been going to a guru, I went to
Ben bir rahibim ve Kurtarıcı uğruna  evlenmedim. Bu yüzden bir guruya gittim, üç ay boyunca ona gittim.
him for three months. He lives near Siloe. Maybe that is the reason, I am not getting Realisation”.
Siloe yakınlarında yaşıyor. Belki de bu yüzden aydınlanmayı elde edemiyorum."
So, I saw the vibrations, I said, “No, he is a Realised soul this guru”.
Ben vibrasyonları gördüm ve "Hayır, bu guru aydınlanmış bir ruh." dedim.
And I took down his address.
Ve adresini aldım.
So he said, “You know,
Sonra şöyle dedi... Biliyorsunuz,
his good friend told me, that he has already told him that ‘I cannot give Realisation.
onun yakın bir dostu Bana şunu söyledi: O, ona zaten demiş ki, "Ben aydınlanma veremem.
And he told about her. She is her Holiness. She is Adi Shakti, everything he told.
Ve O'nun hakkında konuştu. O, Kutsal Efendimiz. O, Adi Shakti. Her şeyi anlattı.
Imagine! This guru.
Düşünsenize! Bu guru.
But the better thing, I’ll tell you.
Ama daha da iyisi var, size anlatayım.
We went to Spain and the girl who came with us, Miriam, was no good for translation.
İspanya'ya gittik ve bizimle gelen kız, Miriam. O, çeviri için pek iyi değildi.
So first day somebody offered his services, he said, “All right, I’ll translate “. He did well.
İlk gün bir kişi yardımcı olmayı teklif etti, "Tamam, ben çeviririm" dedi. İyi iş çıkardı.
But second day, you see, this fellow did not turn up, he was late.
Ama ikinci gün, bu adam gelmedi, geç kaldı.
And one boy – I have got his address also, I think she has got – he turned up.
Ve bir çocuk - adresi de Bende var, sanırım onda da var - geldi.
And he was very good. He organized everything, did everything, he was very good at English
Ve çok iyiydi. Her şeyi organize etti, her şeyi yaptı, İngilizcesi çok iyiydi
and he translated the whole thing very well in Spain and helped.
ve İspanya'da her şeyi çok iyi tercüme etti ve yardımcı oldu.
So, he told these people, “You see, my guru lives on Himalayas.
Bu insanlara şöyle dedi: "Görüyorsunuz, benim gurum Himalayalar'da yaşıyor,
I went and see; some guru Swami or something, Namnemi he told Me.
gidip onu gördüm...'' -Bir guru Swami ya da öyle bir şey... Namnemi Bana söyledi.
And I felt the vibrations were all right.
Ve vibrasyonların iyi olduğunu hissettim.-
And he told me that, ‘You go to Madrid. Mataji is coming there,
''Ve o bana şöyle dedi: Madrid'e git. Mataji oraya geliyor,
go and help her and help her in every way’. “
git ve ona yardım et, her şekilde Ona yardım et."
[Laughter]
Harika!
Great! And then he just disappeared, I never saw him.
Ve sonra birdenbire ortadan kayboldu, onu bir daha hiç görmedim.
And then, of course the hall was so shocking, there were a lot of hikes out there.
Ve sonra, tabii ki salon çok şok ediciydi, dışarıda çok fazla yürüyüş vardı.
But we managed somehow. It’s all right, we managed,
Ama bir şekilde başardık. Sorun yok, başardık,
it’s not difficult, we can manage these things.
zor değil, bu tür şeyleri halledebiliriz.
Only Rome was bit too much, he, Gavin?
Sadece Roma biraz fazla oldu,
[Shri Mataji chuckles]
ha Gavin?
You know, you had to pay that.
Bilirsin, onu ödemek zorundaydın.
Sahaja Yogi: I haven’t paid it back yet, but I’m going to.
Sahaja Yogi: Henüz geri ödemedim ama ödeyeceğim.
Shri Mataji: You’d better not pay them.
Shri Mataji: Onlara ödeme yapsan iyi olur.
Sahaja Yogi: I paid them beforehand.
Sahaja Yogi: Önceden ödedim.
Shri Mataji: Hmm, that’s the problem.
Shri Mataji: Hmm, sorun da bu.
Sahaja Yogi: [Unclear]
Sahaja Yogi: [Anlaşılmıyor]
Shri Mataji: No, I paid for the other things like bill they gave Me, big bill
Shri Mataji: Hayır, Bana verdikleri faturalar gibi diğer şeyleri ödedim,
for the hotel rooms and taxi and this.
otel odaları, taksi ve bunun gibi büyük faturaları.
You see, next day we didn’t know what to do.
Görüyorsunuz, ertesi gün ne yapacağımızı bilmiyorduk.
So, what we did, we took lot of these pamphlets and took a taxi and went round postering them.
Biz de ne yaptık, bu broşürlerden bir sürü aldık, taksiye bindik ve etrafta afişleri astık.
So, it cost us about fifty pounds on the taxi.
Taksiye yaklaşık elli pound ödedik.
[Laughter]
Ama ne yapabilirdik ki,
But what to do, I mean, we didn’t know what to do?
ne yapacağımızı bilmiyorduk.
Because it never appeared.
Çünkü hiç görünmedi.
Sahaja Yogi: You stayed in a hotel room? And you stayed in
Sahaja Yogi: Otel odasında mı kaldınız?
a hotel room? The hotel room is about the most expensive there.
Otel odasında mı kaldınız? Otel odası oradaki en pahalı yerlerden biridir.
Shri Mataji: Very expensive, I tell you! Dinner : for one dinner for both of us, fifteen pounds.
Shri Mataji: Çok pahalı, inan Bana! Akşam yemeği... İkimiz için bir akşam yemeği, on beş pound.
Sahaja Yogi: But you don’t eat in here,
Sahaja Yogi: Ama burada yemek yemiyorsunuz,
you don’t stay in hotels in Italy. No one stays there, unless they’re very, very well off.
İtalya'da otellerde kalmıyorsunuz. Kimse kalmıyor, çok, çok zengin olmadıkça orada kalmaz.
Shri Mataji: I don’t know, then where do you stay? There’s no place.
Shri Mataji: Bilmiyorum, o zaman nerede kalıyorsunuz? Kalacak yer yok.
Sahaja Yogi: Yes.
Sahaja Yogi: Evet.
Shri Mataji: Even in this hotel they had no dinner, you know?
Shri Mataji: Bu otelde bile akşam yemeği yoktu, biliyor musun?
Sahaja Yogi: No, no, they don’t have any.
Sahaja Yogi: Hayır, hayır, hiç yoktu.
Shri Mataji: So they said, “You have to go now to this”.
Shri Mataji: Sonra dediler ki, "Şimdi şuraya gitmeniz gerekiyor."
We said, “We can’t go to far off places where we can get some pizza or something,
Biz de dedik ki, "Uzak yerlere gidip biraz pizza veya bir şeyler alamayız,
you know, to manage further “.
biliyorsunuz, devam edebilmek için.”
So they said, “No, this is nice place, you can go ahead “.
Onlar da dediler ki, "Hayır, burası güzel bir yer, gidebilirsiniz."  Ve on beş pound...
And fifteen pounds, I said, “Very nice for both of us “.
Ben de dedim ki, "İkimiz için de çok güzel."
Seven and a half pounds to however eat.
Yedi buçuk pound da yemek için.
So much, I thought, but they’re very expensive.
Çok fazla diye düşündüm ama çok pahalılar.
Then what we did was to get a pizza, you see.
Sonra yaptığımız şey pizza almaktı, anlarsınız.
But in the night, we just couldn’t do anything.
Ama gece hiçbir şey yapamadık.
Sahaja Yogi: The places to stay in Italy are in the “Pensiones “, they’re very extremely private,
Sahaja Yogi: İtalya'da kalınacak yerler Pensiones'lerde, buralar çok özel yerler,
there are people’s homes, they really aren’t –
insanların evleri, buralar gerçekten…
Shri Mataji: Now we don’t have to worry, Gregoire is going to be posted for ten months.
Shri Mataji: Artık endişelenmemize gerek yok, Gregoire on aylığına görevlendirilecek.
[Shri Mataji chuckles]
Artık sorumluluğu üstlendi.
He has taken the responsibility now. He’s going to work it out.
O bunu halledecek.
[End of recording]
[Kayıt sonu]